- The following is a
conversation with Pavel Durov,
founder and CEO of Telegram,
a messaging platform
actively used by over 1 billion people.
Pavel has spent his life
fighting for freedom of speech,
building tools that
protect human communication
from surveillance and censorship.
For this, he has faced pressure
from some of the most powerful governments
and organizations on earth.
In the face of this immense pressure,
he has always held his ground
continuously fighting
to protect user privacy
and the freedom of all of us humans
to communicate with each other.
I got the chance to spend
a few weeks with him
and can definitively say
that he's one of the most principled
and fearless humans I've ever met.
Plus, when I posted that
I'm hanging out with Pavel,
a lot of people, fans of his,
wrote to me asking if he
does in fact privately live
the disciplined aesthetic
life he's known for,
no alcohol, stoic mindset,
strict diet and exercise,
including a crazy amount of
daily pull-ups and pushups,
no phone except to occasionally
test Telegram features,
and so on.
Yes, he's 100% that guy,
which made the experience
of hanging out with him
really inspiring to me.
I'm grateful for it,
and I'm grateful to now be
able to call him a friend.
This podcast conversation
is in parts philosophical
about freedom, life, human nature,
and the nature of
government bureaucracies,
and it is also in part super technical,
because to me, it's fascinating
that Telegram has a relatively
small engineering team
and yet is able to basically out-innovate
all of its competitors
with an insane rate of
introducing new, unique features.
Just like the meme of "The
Simpsons" did it first,
you consider all the
features we know and love
in our communication apps,
in almost every case,
Telegram did it first.
So we discuss it all,
from the Kafkaesque situation
he's in the midst of in France,
to the rollercoaster
of his life and career,
to his philosophy on technology,
freedom, and the human condition.
And by the way, while
this entire conversation
is in English,
we'll make captions and
voiceover audio tracks
available in multiple languages,
including Russian,
Ukrainian, French, and Hindi.
On YouTube, you can switch
between language audio tracks
by clicking the settings gear icon,
then clicking Audio track,
and then selecting the
language you prefer.
Huge thank you once again to ElevenLabs
for their help with
translation and dubbing
and with the bigger mission
of breaking down barriers
that language creates.
They are truly one of the
most remarkable companies
I've ever had the
pleasure of working with.
This is the "Lex Fridman Podcast."
To support it,
please check out our
sponsors in the description.
And now, dear friends, here's Pavel Durov.
- You've been an advocate for freedom for many
years, writing that you should be ready
to risk everything for
freedom. What were some
influences and insights that helped you
arrive at this value of human freedom?
- I get to experience the difference
between a society with freedom and a
society without freedom pretty
early in life. I was four years old
when my family moved
from the Soviet Union to
northern Italy, and I could see
that a society without freedom
cannot enjoy the abundance of
opinions, of ideas, of goods,
and services. Even for a four
or five year old kid, it was
obvious. That you can't experience all the
toys, the ice cream of sorts, the cartoons
in the Soviet Union that you could access
in Italy. And then I got to realize
something even more important.
You don't get to contribute
to this abundance without freedom. And at
this point, it was pretty obvious to me.
- You also wrote, "Svoboda vazhne
deneg." It translates to:
"Freedom matters more than money." How
do you prevent these values for freedom
corrupted by money, by people with
influence, by people with power?
- Well, the biggest enemies
of freedom are fear and
greed. So you make sure that
they don't stand in your
way. If you imagine the worst thing that
can happen to you, and then make
yourself be comfortable with
it, there's nothing more left to be
afraid of. So you stand your ground,
and you remember that it's worth
living your life according
to the principles that you believe
in, even though this life can end up
being shorter than a longer
life, but lived in slavery.
- Do you contemplate your mortality?
Do you think about your death?
- Oh, yes.
- Are you afraid of it?
- In a way, you have to go
against your instinct of
self-preservation. And
it's not easy. We are all
biological beings hard-coded to be
afraid of death. Nobody wants to die.
But when you approach it
rationally, you live and then you
die. There's no such thing
as your death in your
life. You stop experiencing
life once you die.
So you have to ask yourself this
question, "Is it worth living a
life full of fear of death?" Or, it's
much more enjoyable to forget
about this and live your life
in a way that makes you immune
to this fear, at the same time
remembering that death exists
so that every day would count.
- Yeah. Remembering that death
exists makes you deeply feel
every moment that you do get.
- That's why I love reminding
myself that I can die any day.
- In many ways you live a pretty
stoic existence. I got a chance to
spend a couple of weeks with
you. In many ways, you seek to
minimize the negative effects
of the outside world on your
mind. You've written, quote,
"If you want to reach your full potential
and maintain clarity of mind, stay
away from addictive substances.
My success and health
are the result of 20 plus years
of complete abstinence from
alcohol, tobacco, coffee,
pills, and illegal
drugs. Short-term
pleasure isn't worth your
future." Let's talk about
each one of these. Alcohol.
What's been your philosophy behind that?
- That one is quite easy.
When I was 11 years old, my
biochemistry teacher, he gave
me this book he wrote, it
was called The Illusion
of Paradise. In there, he
would describe the biological and
chemical processes that happen in your
body once you consume this or that
substance. It was mainly related to
illegal drugs, but alcohol was one of
these addictive substances that he
covered. So it turns out that when you drink
alcohol, the thing that happens is that
your brain cells become
paralyzed. They become literally
zombies. And then next day, some time after
the party is over, some of your brain
cells die and never get
to normal. So think about
this. If your brain is this most
valuable tool you have in your
journey to success and happiness, why
would you destroy this tool for short-term
pleasure? This sounds ridiculous.
- In many ways, it's a poison we
let in our body. But by way of
advice, what advice would you give to people
who consider not drinking? You know, a
lot of people use alcohol to enable
them to have a vibrant social
life. There's a lot of
pressures from society,
you know, at a party to drink so they can
socialize. So, what advice
would you give to them,
To people who imagine having a
social life without alcohol?
- Well, first of all, don't be afraid
to be contrarian. Set your own rules.
Secondly, if you feel you
need to drink, there must
be some problem you're trying to
conceal. There's something that, some
fear you're not ready to confront,
and you have to address this fear.
If there is a good-looking girl
you're afraid to approach,
get rid of this fear, approach her,
practice, do it again and again. It's pretty
banal... but this advice works.
- Fix the underlying problem, which
is usually at the very bottom is
always going to be fear. Work on that.
- I don't know. Very often, people are trying
to escape something in their lives with
alcohol. What is it they're
trying to escape? What is this
problem? You have to get to the bottom
of it. Your mind is trying to tell you
something valuable, and instead of
addressing it directly, you are
flooding it in alcohol, which is sort
of a spiritual painkiller, but works
only temporarily, and then you have
to pay the debt with interest.
- So, what do you do? I mean, you've
been in a lot of gatherings, a lot of
parties. Is there some
challenges to saying no?
- For me, not at all. I've been always ready
to stand my ground and say no when I feel
something's not right. And
it's extraordinary how easily
we humans are affected by what we perceive
as majority, because nobody since ancient
times, since millions of
years ago, wants to be left
out by the tribe. We are scared that we
won't become accepted anymore, which
thousands or millions of years ago
meant we're going to starve to
death. So, we have to consciously
fight this inclination
to be agreeable with everything that
the majority imposes on you, because
it's quite clear that many things that the
majority... in many activities
the majority is engaging in
are not bringing you any good.
- So, that's another fear you have
to face. Going into a party and
the fear of being the outcast at
that party, of being different than
others at that party, at that
social gathering in the crowd
of humans, be different. That's a fear.
- That's a fear, and it's quite
irrational if you think about it.
It was something that made a
lot of sense 20,000 years ago.
It makes zero sense today,
because if you think about it, if
you do the same thing everybody
else around you is doing,
you don't have any competitive advantage,
and you don't get to become outstanding
at some point in your life.
- Yeah, that's one of the
things we talked about
sort of by way of advice is, if you want
to be successful in life, you want to be
different.
- Definitely.
- And perhaps, I think you
said you want to achieve
mastery at a niche, so find
a niche at which you can
pursue with all your effort
and achieve mastery,
and the niche being
different than anything that
anybody else is doing. Can you
explain that a little bit more?
- So, obviously, in order to
contribute to the society
you're in, to the economy
of the country you live
in, you have to do something
that is valuable. But
if you're doing something that
everybody else is doing anyway,
what's the value of it?
Now, it sounds easier
than it is done to do something
that nobody else is doing,
because we humans are surrounded
by all kinds of information
which makes us want to copy what we are
perceiving. At the same time, there
are so many areas which you can
explore that have nothing to do with the
information you receive on
the daily basis. So, it's
extremely important to curate the
information sources that you have,
so that you wouldn't be
somebody who is left to
the will of AI-based algorithmic
feed telling you what's
important, so that you
end up consuming the same
information, the same stuff, the same
memes, the same news as everybody
else. But rather, you should be
proactive. You should deliberately try to
set a goal an area that you want to
explore, and then actively search
information that is relevant to
this field, so that one day,
you can become the world's number one
expert in this field. And it's
not quite... it's not that
difficult to do that. You have to
just remain consistent, because
nobody else is trying to do
that. Everybody else is just reading
the same news and discussing the same
news every day. But this way, they don't
get to have a competitive advantage.
- Yeah. The majority of the
population become slaves to the
AI recommender systems, AI-driven
recommender systems, and so the
content everybody's fed is the same
thing, and we all become the same.
On that point, one of the
different things you do is you
don't use a phone, except
occasionally to test Telegram
features. But I've been with you for
two weeks. I haven't seen you use a
phone at all in the way that most
people use a phone, like, for their
social media. So, can you describe
your philosophy behind that?
- I don't think a phone is
a necessary device. I
remember growing up, I
didn't have a mobile phone.
When I was a student at the
university, I didn't have a mobile
phone. When I finally got
to use a mobile phone, I
never used phone calls. I was always
in airplane mode or mute. I hated the
idea of being disturbed. My philosophy
here is pretty simple. I want to define
what is important in my
life. I don't want other
people or companies, all kinds of
organizations telling me what is
important today and what
I should be thinking about. Just
set up your own agenda, and
the phone gets in your way.
- It provides distractions.
It guides what you
should be looking at, what you will be looking
at, so you don't want that. You want to
quiet the mind. You want to choose what
kind of stuff you let inside your mind.
- Yes, because this way I can contribute
to the progress of society, or at
least I like to think this way, and
this makes me happier.
- How often do you find quiet time
to just think and focus deeply on
work without any distractions? You mentioned
to me that you value quiet mornings.
- Yes. So the thing I'm trying to do, I
try to allocate as much time as possible
for sleep. Now, even if
I allocate, say, 11 or
12 hours for sleep, I won't
sleep for 11 or 12 hours.
So what I end up doing is I end up
lying in bed thinking, and
some people hate it. They
say, "Oh, you have to take a sleeping
pill," but I never take pills.
I love these moments. I get
so many brilliant ideas, or at
least they seem brilliant to me at
the moment, while I'm lying in bed, either
late in the evening or early in the morning.
That's my favorite time of the day.
Sometimes I wake up, I go take
a shower, still without the
phone. Beautiful ideas can come to you
while you're doing your
morning exercise, your
morning routine, without a phone. If you
open your phone first thing in the morning,
what you end up being
is a creature that is
told what to think about for the rest
of the day. Same is true in a way if
you've been consuming news from
social media late at night.
But then how do you define
what is important and
what you really want to become
in life? Now, I'm not saying
you have to completely stay
away from all sources of
information, but take some time
to think about what's really
important for you and what you
want to change in this world.
- So you definitely try to avoid digital devices
for as many hours as possible in the morning,
just to have the quiet thinking
time? Plus the crazy amounts of
push-ups and squats.
- I know it's kind of
counterintuitive because
I founded one of the largest social
networks in the world, after which I
founded the second-largest
messaging app in the world, and
you're supposed to be
really connected. But the
conclusion you reach very early
is that the more connected and
accessible you are, the
less productive you are.
And then how can you run this
thing if you're constantly
bombarded by all kinds of information,
most of which is irrelevant to the success
of what you're trying to build? You
know, the entire world can be fascinated
by a fight, a quarrel between
the world's richest man and
the world's most powerful man. But
for the vast majority of these people
following this saga, it's irrelevant.
It won't change their lives.
And in any case, they can't affect it, so
it's a bit pointless. Of course, there are
people who are engaged in activities
that require them to be up-to-date
of everything that's going
on, but 99% of people aren't.
- Yeah. The internet, social
media presents to us drama
in such a way that we think it's the biggest
thing in the world, the most important thing in
which the tides of history will
turn when in reality, most things
will not turn the tides of history.
And so, I guess our challenge
is to figure out what is
the timeless thing? What is
the thing that's happening today that's
still going to be true in 10, 20
years? And from that,
decide what you're going to do. And
that's very difficult on social media
'cause everybody's outraged. The news
of the day, whatever the quarrel is,
that's the thing that everyone
thinks the world will end because
of this thing, and then another
thing happens the next day.
- And they're trying to
influence your emotions.
And that's how you get into trouble, because
you can be forced to make conclusions
that are not in your best interest.
- I've seen you be, once again,
quite stoic about your
emotions. Do you ever get
angry? Do you ever get
lonely? You ever get sad?
The rollercoaster of human
emotion. And what do you do with that?
What do you make difficult decisions?
- I'm a human being like everybody
else. I do get to experience
emotions, and some of them
are not very pleasant. But I
believe that it's the
responsibility of every one of us-
...to cope with these
emotions and to learn to
work through them.
Self-discipline is particularly
important, because without
it, how can you overcome
this seemingly endless
loop of negativity or
despair that ultimately leads to depression
for some people? I normally never
have depression. I don't remember
having depression in the last 20
years at least, maybe when I was a teenager.
But one of the reasons for that is, I
start doing things. I identify the
problem, I can see a solution, and I start
executing the strategy. If
you are stuck in this loop of
being worried about something,
nothing's ever going to change.
And people often make this mistake,
thinking, "Oh, I should just
have some rest and then
regain energy." This is
not how it works. You gain energy by doing
something. So if you start doing
something, then it happens. You
feel motivated, you feel inspired,
and then ultimately you do
something else, a little bit more, a
little bit more, and in a few years,
who knows, you may end up
achieving great things.
- Yeah, that's the thing that people
really confuse. If you're stuck
in a depressive cycle,
even when you really,
really, really, really don't
wanna do anything, just do
something. Try to make progress
because the good feeling comes
in the end of that. The whole point is to do
first and then feel, not feel and then do.
- Exactly. And going to the
gym is a good example.
There are many days when you
don't want to start working
out, but you have to overcome
this initial reluctance, and
then you get to a point that
you enjoy it, and you think,
"Oh my God, it was such a good idea
to come to the gym today." But
it's similar to pretty much every
activity. You get to write some
code, write a small
piece of code first, and
then you get inspired.
Then you come up with more
ideas. You need to write a novel
or just write the program.
This is pretty obvious, and
it's not a secret, but because
we are bombarded with all kinds
of information that is not really
important for us in terms of becoming
successful, we often forget the important
things, and this is one of them.
- We've been working out every single day.
You have been working out for many years
pretty intensively, so I think
a lot of people would love to
know what's your perfect
daily workout regimen,
let's say on a daily, on a weekly basis?
- I do 300 push-ups and 300
squats every morning, and in
addition to that, I go to
the gym normally five or six
times a week, spending between
one and two hours every day.
- So push-ups and squats are still
a big part of your routine?
- Yes, this is how I start
my day. I'm not sure they
do a lot in terms of changing your body,
but they're definitely a good way to
practice self-discipline,
because you don't want to do these
push-ups in the morning most of the days.
Squats are particularly
boring. They're not that
hard. They're just boring. But you
overcome it, and then it's much easier to
start doing other things related
to your work, for example. When I
can, I also take an ice bath
because it's another exercise of
self-discipline. I think the main
muscle you can exercise is this
muscle, the muscle of
self-discipline. You know,
not your biceps or your
pecs or anything else,
because if you get to train that one,
everything else just comes by itself.
- Yeah, everything else becomes easy.
We should mention, I went with you
to Banya, and I think it's
fair to say you're nuts
in terms of how much you
can handle, and I didn't
even see the worst of it. Can you just
speak to your crazy escapades in the Banya,
what value you get from it, so
both the heat and the cold?
- I don't know if it's crazy. I think it's
quite natural and normal by this time.
But maybe I just got used to it.
So Banya is this extreme kind of
sauna practiced by Eastern Europeans.
But it is done in a way that
maximizes heat, and they also
use all kinds of herbs and branches, and
it's a much more holistic and natural
experience. Then a necessary
part of it is you get the cold
plunge, and then you go back. And
again, this is one of those
things that maybe in the moment
is not always that pleasant,
particularly if you go to extreme
temperatures. You don't
feel great. I don't always
feel great, but this feeling is
passing. It's only a few minutes.
Same with the ice bath.
You have to suffer a bit,
and then you get to feel great
for hours and days after.
What's more, it gives you these
long-term health benefits. In a
way, you can look at it as alcohol in
reverse. Alcohol will give
you this short, fleeting
pleasure for an hour, for a couple of
hours, but then you will be paying
for it with long-term negative consequences.
I'd rather do Banya and ice bath.
- We swam the length of a large lake
in France a couple times. Can you
talk through why you value
these multi-hour swims?
- I love swimming for hours. The longest
I swam was five and a half hours in
Finland, it was quite cold.
I got lost in the process,
barely could find my way back. But
the reason I do it, yes, you feel
great after. You're shaking a little
bit, but you feel great after. We
cross a huge lake, and I cross many
lakes, Geneva Lake, Zurich Lake. And
every time, you feel this achievement
which makes you happy, makes you
feel strong, and then you're
more ready to other challenges. And of
course, when you know you are going to start
a journey that will last a few
hours, you're reluctant to do
it. But you swim for 10 minutes, and then
for 20 minutes, and then for 30 minutes,
and it teaches you this
incredible patience
that I think is necessary if you
want to achieve anything in life.
- And it's pretty meditative,
lake versus ocean.
- Yes. And you don't have to go too fast.
You can be slow and enjoy the moment.
- Until you get lost, and it's five and a
half hours. Did you panic if you were
gonna be able to find the
shore or find your way out?
- Not really. I'm a reasonably stress-resilient
person. I didn't panic at that moment,
and there were worse swims I
had that were shorter, but
involved accidents, and you
know about some of them. So
that wasn't the worst by
far. But an important thing
about swimming and physical activity in
general is that it makes your mind clear,
and your thinking process is becoming
more efficient. Because at the end
of the day, the efficiency of our brain is
limited by how much sugar and oxygen our
heart can push through blood to
our brain. So how can you make
this go faster, or how do you make your
lungs more efficient? How do you make
your heart more efficient in
doing that? Physical activity is
the only way I know of. So
it's not just staying healthy
or trying to look good. It's also
being productive. It's also being
stress-resilient. All of these qualities
are necessary if you want to run a large
company, if you want to start a company.
I'm surprised, when I started doing this
more than 10 years ago, that more
CEOs didn't engage in sports.
The situation changed in the
last several years, which is
great. Because back in the day, if you take
20 years ago, there was this stereotype
that if you were strong, you
must be not very smart, and vice
versa, which is complete lunacy. Very
often, these two things go together.
- So for you, working out is not just about staying
healthy. It's actually valuable for the work that
you do as a tech leader, as an
engineer, as a technologist?
- Oh, yes. When I can't
train, I can instantly feel
that stress is creeping on me. Like...
So even in situations where I'm
constrained, I can't go to the
gym, I just keep doing push-ups.
I just keep doing squats.
- Yeah. I mean, that's the cool thing
about bodyweight exercise, you
can just do it anywhere.
You could just pop
off 50 or 100 push-ups before a meeting.
- Don't you feel weird when you have
a day without physical activity?
- Yeah. If I go a day without doing
push-ups, at the very minimum,
that's a shitty day.
- And if you can do pull-ups,
it's even better.
- Yeah. I gotta ask you about
your diet, too. No processed
sugar, no fast food, no soda,
intermittent fasting sometimes
once a day only, sometimes a
couple times a day. So take me
through your philosophy on the no
sugar, no soda, just clean food.
- Well, sugar is pretty easy,
because it's addictive.
The more you consume sugar, the more
you want it, the hungrier you get.
So if you want to stay
efficient and healthy,
why consume processed sugar? You'll
just end up snacking all the time.
Intermittent fasting,
eating only within six
hours or not eating for 18
hours every day also brings
structure into your day and
into your eating habits, so you
don't crave sugar anymore. Because,
you know, if you eat sugar and
then you're unable to snack, you're just
punishing yourself. I read a few books on
longevity. I think something
everybody agrees on is that sugar is
harmful. Now, I'm not militant about
sugar. You can eat berries, fruit, if you
feel your body needs it.
But it's not true to think
it's necessary to consume
sweet things, not for
children, not for adults. Red meat, I
stopped eating it about 20 years
ago, because I just felt heavy
every time I had it. So I
guess it's individual. It's my
metabolism, my digestive system
isn't agreeing with this kind of
food. So I normally eat seafood of
all kinds and vegetables. This is
the basic source of calories for me.
- Yeah, and like all things you
said, short-term pleasure isn't
worth your future. So, a lot of things we
all know, that alcohol is destructive to the
body, tobacco, pills, processed food, sugar.
But society puts that on you, makes it
very difficult to avoid. So, I guess
it all boils down to just discipline.
- Yes, and trying to identify the
real cause of an issue you're
experiencing. If you're experiencing a
headache, one solution would be to take
a pill, and then the headache disappears.
What this pill would actually do, in most
cases, it would mute the consequence,
your feeling of pain. It's a painkiller.
It will not eliminate the root
cause, so you have to ask
yourself, "What is it that is causing
this headache? Do I need to drink some
water? Is the air quality here bad?
Do I need to start getting more
sleep? Is there something
wrong with people around me
that are stressing me out?" There
must be some reason why you're
experiencing a headache.
But if you take a pill,
you're not removing this reason. You're
actually making it worse, because this
harmful factor is still there. It's
like you're piloting a helicopter,
and there are some red signals,
some red lamps start to blink
and it starts producing bad, unpleasant
noise. What would you do?
You would try to figure
out the cause and eliminate
it. Maybe there is some
mountain next to you and you have
to avoid it, or you take a hammer
and smash the signal.
I think the good answer is quite
obvious. So, why are we constantly doing
this regardless? Well, because everybody
else is doing it, because there's a whole
industry trying to persuade
you that this is the right
thing to do. So it's incredibly important
to analyze yourself and try to
get to the bottom of things.
- So, you generally try to avoid all
pills, all pharmaceutical products?
- Yes. I've been staying away
from all of that since
I became an adult. When you're a
teenager, your mom would typically
say, "We need to take this pill,
otherwise, you know, the world collapses."
Once I became a grown-up, I said, "No, I
don't think that the producers of pills are
incentivized in the right way."
They are not really interested in
eliminating the root of the problem.
They would rather have me dependent on
the pills they're producing
so that I could buy them
forever. And then I also
realized... No, I'm not saying
that you should never take pills.
There are obviously some diseases
that you can only fight with
antibiotics, for example,
so I'm not suggesting we go
back to the Middle Ages.
But what I'm saying is we overuse pills.
- Yeah, it's always good to study and deeply
understand the incentives under which
the world operates
so that you don't get swept up into
the forces that operate under these
incentives. And big pharma
is certainly one of
them. Pharmaceutical companies
have a huge incentive to keep the
problem going versus solving
the problem. It's wise.
- Well, this is something
I practice every day. I
read some piece of news, and I ask myself,
"Who benefits from me reading this?"
then you can end up coming
to this conclusion that
maybe 95% of things we read
in the news have been written
and published because somebody
wanted you to buy some product,
support some political cause, fight some
war, donate some money, just do something
that would benefit other people.
And this is not a problem
to support causes that
you truly believe in, as
long as it was your intentional choice,
and you're not being manipulated
into fighting other people's wars.
- And that takes us back to the original
thing we started talking about, which is
freedom. One of the ways to
achieve freedom of thought is to
remove your mind from the influences, the
forces that manipulate you. That's really
important to realize. The content you
consume, especially on the internet,
when a large percentage of it
is designed to manipulate your mind,
you have to disconnect yourself
and be very proactive, understanding
what the bias is, what the incentives
are, so you can think clearly,
independently, and objectively.
- And again, it ties back with
restraint from alcohol.
Because if your mind is
clouded, how can you
analyze yourself? You'll always be
dependent on opinions of others. You will
always follow the mainstream, and w-
then whatever the authorities
or whoever in charge
will tell you, you'll believe it,
because you don't have a tool
of your own to rely on to
come to your own conclusions.
- I have to ask you, this is something
that came up. You don't watch
porn. I don't think I've heard you
talk about this before. What's the
philosophy behind not watching porn? You
know, there's a lot of people that talk
about porn in general having a
very negative effect on young men,
on their view of the world, on their
development of their sexuality, and how
they get into relationships, and
all that kind of stuff. So what's
your philosophy in not consuming porn?
- I don't watch porn because
I just feel it's a
surrogate, a substitute
for the real thing that
is not necessary in my life.
If anything, it just forces
you to exchange some energy,
some inspiration, to a fleeting
moment of pleasure. It doesn't
make sense. And i- in any case, as I
said, it's not the real
thing. So as long as you
can access the real thing,
you don't need to watch
porn. But then, if you can't
access the real thing,
it's... you shouldn't watch
porn as well, because it
means there's some deficiency in your life,
some problem that you have to overcome.
- Yeah, analyze the underlying cause.
And again, this goes back to
the theme of investing in a
long-term flourishing versus
short-term pleasure. There's a theme
to the way you approach life.
- I try to be strategic. I try to act
under the assumption that I'm not
going to die in one hour from
now, and I'm going to stick
around for a bit, despite
the fact that we are all
mortal. So why would I
exchange the mid and long-term for the
short-term? Doesn't make any sense.
- Quick pause, bathroom break.
- Yeah, let's take a break.
- All right, we took a break, and now we're
back. I gotta ask you about Telegram,
the company. I got to meet some of the
brilliant engineers that work there.
Telegram runs lean. Relative
to other technology
companies that achieve the scale that
Telegram does, it has very few employees.
So how many people are on the core team,
let's say the core engineering team?
- The core engineering team is
about 40 people. This includes
backend, frontend designers,
system administrators.
- Can you speak to the philosophy behind
running a company with so few employees?
- Well, what we realized
really early is that
quantity of employees doesn't translate
to quality of the product they
produce. In many cases, it's the opposite.
If you have too many people, they have
to coordinate their efforts, constantly
communicate, and 90% of
their time will be spent on
coordinating the small pieces of work
they're responsible for between each other.
The other problem with having
too many employees is that
some of them won't get
enough work to do. And if
they don't get enough work to do, they
demotivate everybody else by their mere
existence. They're still there,
they're still getting the
salary, but they don't do
anything. And if they don't do
anything, more often than not,
they will start trying to
find their purpose elsewhere,
maybe inside your team,
but not by doing productive work, but
by finding problems that don't exist
within the team. And that
can disrupt the team and
the mood inside it even
further. Also, when you
intentionally don't allow
some of your team members
to hire more people to help them, they
will be forced to automate things. In
our case, you know, we have
tens of thousands of servers around the
world, almost 100,000, distributed across
several continents and data centers.
If you try to manage this system
manually without automation,
you will probably end up hiring thousands
of people, tens of thousands of people.
But if you rely on algorithms
and the team is forced to
put together algorithms in order to
manage it, then it becomes much more
scalable, and much more efficient, and
interestingly, much more reliable as well.
- And more resilient to the
changing geopolitics, to
the changing technology, all of
that. Because if you automate
the distributed aspect of
the data storage and all the
compute, then that's going to be resilient
to everything the world throws at
you. I suppose if you have people managing
all of it, it becomes stale quickly.
- Yes. Humans are attack vectors. And
if you have a distributed system
that runs itself automatically, you have a
a chance at increasing the security
and speed of your service.
and speed of your service. This
is what we did with Telegram,
while also making it much more
reliable. Because if some part
of the network goes down,
can still switch to the other parts of it.
- Yeah. One of the big ways
to protect user privacy
is that you store the data. The
infrastructure side of Telegram
infrastructure side of Telegram is
distributed across many legal jurisdictions
many legal jurisdictions with the decryption
keys. So it's encrypted in the cloud,
keys. So it's encrypted in the
cloud, the decryption keys are split
and kept in different locations so
that no single government or entity
entity can access the data. Can you
explain the strength of this approach?
- The way we designed Telegram is
we never wanted to have any humans,
any employees have any access
to private messaging data. That's why since 2012,
when we've been trying to come up with this design,
been trying to come up with this design,
we always invested a lot of effort
invested a lot of effort into making
sure that nobody can mess with it.
into making sure that nobody can mess
with it. Like if you hire an employee
employee or any of the existing
employee, they can't break the system
they can't break the system in a way that
would allow them to access messages of users.
access messages of users. And then of course,
we launched end-to-end encrypted messaging
end-to-end encrypted messaging that is even
more protected, but it has certain limitations,
but it has certain limitations, so you still have
to rely on encrypted cloud. So an interesting
encrypted cloud. So an interesting
engineering challenge was how do you make
sure that no point of failure can be created
that no point of failure can be
created within your team or outside?
- So no employee can even access user messages. So
that's the thing. You know, we talk about encryption,
thing. You know, we talk about encryption, we talk about
privacy, we talk about security, all these kinds of things.
all these kinds of things. I think the number one thing
that people are concerned about, about which there's also
about which there's also misinformation, is about
private messages. So Telegram is very, very protective
of the private messages of users. So you're saying
saying employees never can
access the private messages.
Have any governments or intelligence agencies
ever accessed private user messages in the past?
agencies ever accessed private
user messages in the past?
- No, never. Telegram has never shared
a single private message with anyone,
a single private message with anyone, including
governments and intelligence services.
including governments and intelligence services. If
you try to access any server in any of the data center
data center locations, it's all encrypted.
You can extract all the hard drives
and analyze it, but you won't get anything. It's
all encrypted in a way that is undecipherable.
It's all encrypted in the
way that is undecipherable.
That was very important for us.
That's why we can say with confidence
there hasn't been ever a leakage of
data, any leak of data from Telegram.
Not in terms of private messages,
not in terms of, say, contact lists.
- Do you see in the future a possible scenario
where you might share user private messages
with governments or with intelligence agencies?
- No. We designed the system in
a way that it's impossible.
impossible. It would require us to change the system,
and we won't do that because we made a promise to our
and we won't do that because
we made a promise to our
We would rather shut Telegram down
in a certain country than do that.
- So that's one of the principles
you operate under: you're going to
protect user privacy.
- I think it's fundamental. Without the right
to privacy, people can't feel fully free
and protected.
- I mean, this is a good place to ask.
I'm sure you're pressured by all
kinds of people, all kinds
of organizations to share
private data. Where do
you find the strength
and the fearlessness to say
no to everybody, including
powerful intelligence agencies, including
powerful governments, influential powerful
people?
- I guess part of it is just
me being me. I stood up
for myself and for my values
since I was a little kid.
I had issues with my
teachers because I would
point out their mistakes during
classes. And at the end of
the day, what's important is to remind
yourself that you have nothing to lose.
They can think they blackmail you with
something, they can threaten you with something.
But what is it they really can do to you?
Worst case, they can kill you. But that brings
us back to the first part of our discussion.
But that brings us back to the
first part of our discussion.
There's no point living your life in fear.
As for Telegram, it's
incredibly successful. But if
we lose one market or two markets,
or pretty much all of the markets,
I don't care that much. It won't affect
me, it won't affect my lifestyle in any
way. I will still be doing
my push-ups, you know? So...
You don't like encryption, you
don't like privacy, you think you
should ban encryption in your
country, like the European Union
is trying to do now for
all the member states.
Well, go ahead and do
that. We'll just quit this
market. We won't operate there. It's
not that important. They all think that
somehow we profit from their citizens
and the only goal tech companies have is
extracting revenues. And it's true,
most tech companies are like this.
But there are projects like
Telegram which are a bit
different. And I'm not
sure they realize that.
- So for you, the value of
maintaining your integrity
in relation to your principles is
more important than anything else.
And of course, we should say
that you also have full ability and
control to do just that because
you, Pavel Durov, own 100% of
Telegram. So there's nobody else
with a say on this question.
- There are no shareholders,
which is quite unique.
- Very unique. I don't think there's anything
even close to that in any major tech
company.
- And this allows us to
operate the way we operate.
build this project and
maintain it based on certain
fundamental principles which, by the
way, I think everybody believes in.
I think the right to privacy
is included in the constitution
of most countries, at least most
Western countries. But
it's still under attack
almost every week, and
it often starts with
well-meaning proposals: "Oh,
we have to fight crime.
We have to do that. We have to protect
the children." But at the end of
the day, the result is the
same. People lose their right
to such a fundamental thing as privacy.
They sometimes lose their right
to express themselves, to assemble,
and this is a slippery slope
that we witnessed in pretty
much every autocratic
country, or country that used to be
free and then became autocratic.
No dictator in the world ever said, "Let's
just strip you away from your rights
because I want more power to myself and I
want you to be miserable."
They all justified it
with very reasonable-sounding justifications,
and then it came in stages, gradually.
And after a few years, people
would find themselves in
a position when they're helpless.
They can't protest. Every
message they send is monitored.
They can't assemble. It's over.
- So you see Telegram as a place
that people from all walks of
life, from every nation can have a place
to speak their mind, to
have a voice. In the
context, in the geopolitical context
that you're mentioning that governments
when they become autocratic,
naturally it's the way of the
world, human nature and the nature of
governments, they become more censorious.
They begin to censor, and
always justifying it in their
minds perhaps assuming
that they are doing good.
- Perhaps some of them assume
they are doing good, but
interestingly, it always results in the
state accumulating more power at the
expense of the individual. And then
where does it stop? You know, we
humans are not very good
at finding the right
balance, and in this case, the
right balance between chaos
and order, between freedom and
structure. We tend to go to extremes.
- I think you still consider yourself a
libertarian. There is something about
government that always, over time,
naturally builds a larger and larger
bureaucracy, and in that
machine of bureaucracy, it
accumulates more and more power. And
it's not always that some one individual
member of that bureaucracy
is the one that corrupts the initial principles
on which the government was founded, but
just something over time, you forget.
You begin to censor. You begin to limit
the freedoms of the individual,
the ability of the individuals
to speak, to have a voice, to vote.
It just gradually happens that way.
- And the government is not some
abstract notion. The government
consists of people, and these people
have goals. They would naturally be
inclined to increase
their level of influence,
to have more subordinates,
to have more resources,
and that's how you end up in an endless
loop of, you know, ever-increasing
taxes, ever-increasing regulation,
which ultimately just suffocates
free market, free enterprise,
and free speech. So, you
do want to have very, very strict
limitations on the extent the
government can increase its
powers at the expense of
citizens. Ironically, you
don't have those limitations.
You're supposed to, in all countries
which are considered to be free.
It's supposed to be the Constitution
that protects everybody,
but interestingly, it doesn't always
work this way. They are able to find
very tricky phrasings in order
to carve out exceptions,
and then the exception becomes the rule.
- On this topic,
I'd love to talk to you about the
recent saga of you being arrested in
August of last year in France.
I think I should say that
it's one of the worst overreaches of power
I've seen as applied to a tech leader in
recent history, in all history.
So it's tragic, but I think
speaks to the thing that we've
been talking about. So
maybe can you tell the full
saga what happened? You
arrive in France...
- I arrived in France last year in
August just for a short two-day trip,
and then I see a dozen armed policemen
greeting me and asking me to follow
them. They read me a list of something like
15 serious crimes that I'm accused of,
which was mind-boggling. At first, I
thought there must be some mistake. Then I
realized they're being serious,
and they're accusing me of all possible
crimes that the users of Telegram have
allegedly committed, or some users. And they
think I should be responsible for this,
which again, like you said, is something
that never happened in the history
of this planet. No country, not even an
authoritarian one, did that
to any tech leader, at
least at this scale. There are good reasons
for that, because you're sacrificing
a big part of your economic growth
by sending these kinds of messages
to the business and tech
community. So they put me in
a police car, and I found
myself in police custody.
A small room, no windows.
Just a narrow bed
made of concrete. I spent
almost four days there.
In the process, I had to
answer some questions of the
policemen. They were interested
in how Telegram operates.
Most of it is public
anyway, and I was struck by
very limited understanding, or should
I say, even a lack of understanding
on behalf of the people who initiated
this investigation against me about how
technology works, how encryption
works, how social media work.
- I mean, there's something darkly
poetic about a tech founder of a
platform where a billion people are
communicating with each other, and
you're on concrete, no pillow, for days,
no windows. It's like a book. I mean,
it reminds me, I'm a huge fan of Franz
Kafka, and he's written about
the absurdity of these kinds of
situations, hence the Kafkaesque
stories. There's a story
literally about the situation
that he wrote, perhaps predicted,
called "The Trial," where a
person is arrested for no
reason that anybody can explain
and is stuck in the judicial
system for a long time. Fascinatingly,
in that story, neither the person
arrested nor any individual
member of the system itself
fully understands what is happening.
Nobody can truly answer the questions,
and eventually the person,
spoiler alert, is mentally broken
by the whole system, which is
what bureaucracy can do in
its most absurd forms. It breaks the spirit,
the human spirit latent in all of us.
That's the negative side of bureaucracy.
- I agree with you on the absurdity of
this thing, because if this was a
good faith attempt to fix an issue,
there were so many ways
to reach out to Telegram,
to reach out to me personally,
voice their concerns, and solve
any alleged problem in a way that is
conventional and diplomatic, the way every
other country on this
planet solves its problems,
including with Telegram, and
we did it dozens of times.
- Yeah, you have a nice page showing this.
This is kind of like details that most
people don't really think about. But
Telegram was at the forefront of
moderating CSAM and terrorist groups. There's
a nice page, telegram.org/moderation,
that shows just the incredible
amount of groups and
channels that are engaged in
terrorist activity and CSAM
activity that are blocked,
actively blocked, found and
blocked by Telegram. And a lot of this work,
like you said, because of the automation
that's done with machine learning,
just the scale is insane. This
is stuff that most noobs like me who are
just chatting it up on Telegram don't
think about. But there's
just an immense number of
people essentially doing
things that violate the
law on there, and you have to find
them immediately and catch it. I guess
all platforms have to deal with it,
and Telegram was doing a great job of
dealing with that kind of content. And what
you're saying is the French government
had no idea.
- Do they even know what
machine learning is?
- It's a concept that is
challenging to explain to them,
but I think they will learn much
more about it by the end of this
investigation. That's my hope.
In any case, you're right. I mean, if you
look at Telegram, we've been fighting
harmful content that is publicly
distributed on our platform
since 10 years ago, actually, since the
time we launched public
channels on Telegram. And since
something like eight years ago,
we had daily transparency reports
on how many channels related to
child abuse or terrorist propaganda
we've taken down daily. Every day, we've
taken like, maybe hundreds of them.
And if you include all kinds of content
that we remove, all the accounts,
groups, channels, posts,
that would amount to
millions of pieces of content every
week, hundreds of thousands every day.
And then somebody would read
the newspaper, get enraged
because they would read something about
child porn, and this is a subject that
is very emotionally charged, and start
doing something not based on data
and logical thinking and laws, but based
on emotions driven from inaccurate input.
- Yeah, I think we should make it pretty clear
that there's no world, no reason that the
French government should have arrested you,
but here we are. That's the situation you're
in. So to be clear, you have
to show up in front of a
judge. Now all of this is beautifully
absurd. It would be hilarious if it wasn't
extremely serious. You have to
show up in front of a judge
every certain amount of time. And
what is that experience like?
- In France, they have this role of
investigative judge. I don't think you have it
in many other places in the
world. It means I'm not on trial,
I'm being investigated.
And in France, it's not just the
police or prosecutor asking me
questions, it's a judge, which,
in my experience, is more like
still a prosecutor, but it's called a judge,
and that makes it harder to appeal. So
if you're limited in, say,
countries where you can
travel, then to appeal that restriction
will take you a lot of time.
The investigation itself should have never
been started. It's an absurd and harmful
way of solving an issue as complicated as
regulating social media.
It's just the wrong tool.
So we objected and
appealed the investigation
itself. We did last year, I
believe. We're still not even given
a hearing date for the appeal, because
the process is painfully slow,
not just for me but for
everybody, which made
me realize the system may be
broken on many levels. You have
other entrepreneurs affected
by the French justice system
telling me horror stories about
their experiences, where businesses
got paralyzed by very unnecessary actions
of investigative judges that ended
up being unjustified and biased. And in
the end, you can perhaps solve it when
you reach a higher court
and you'll get justice, but you'll lose
a lot of time and energy in the process.
So this is the only thing
that is, I hope, different,
and will be different in this case
compared to the story you told from Kafka.
- I mean, but it does, as Kafka
describes, break a lot of people
with time. So when do you hope...
We should say that you were
for a long time not allowed
to travel out of France. Now
you can travel to Dubai.
We're now in Dubai. Got to
meet many of the people
that work at Telegram.
Telegram is headquartered in Dubai. But
you're not allowed to travel anywhere
else. When do you think you're coming to
Texas to hang out with me over there?
- That's a hard question to answer because
it doesn't depend on just my actions.
I can just say this: I am patient. I
will not let this limitation on my
freedom dictate my actions. I will,
if anything, double down on defending
freedoms because I experienced firsthand
what the absence of freedom feels like, at
least during those four days in
police custody when you are stuck,
just stuck, unable to
communicate with people
that are important to you. When you don't
even know what's going on in the world
in relation to you personally.
So I have no crystal ball that
would tell me the future.
I can't say that I'm
pessimistic. I think we've
been able to gradually remove
most of the restrictions initially
imposed on my freedom last August.
- If the French government or
the French intelligence agency
want to have a backdoor to
access private user messages,
what would you say to them? Is there
anything they can do to get access
to the private user messages?
- Nothing. My response would
be very clear... but it
won't be very polite, so I'm not sure.
- It's good to say here.
- It's good to say because
you're wearing a tie and-
- Yeah. This is a serious
adult gentleman-like
program. But it is a concern
that people have is when
you have so much pressure from
governments, that over time, they'll
wear you down and you'll give in.
And then, of course, other places
use that as propaganda, try to attack you.
You get attacked by basically every nation.
So it's a difficult
medium in which to operate. It's
difficult to be you, fighting for
freedom, fighting to preserve people's
privacy. But is there something you could say
to reassure people that
you're not going to sacrifice
any of the principles that
you've just expressed? If the
French government just
keeps wearing you down?
- I think the French government is losing
this battle. This battle is wrong.
The more pressure I get, the more
resilient and defiant I become.
And I think I have proven
that in the last several
months, when there were attempts to use my
situation, being stuck here in France, by
approaching me and asking me to do things
in other countries,
blocking certain channels,
changing the way Telegram
works. And not only I
refused, I told the world about it, and
I'm going to keep telling the world
about every instance
any government, in this case, in
particular, the French government,
tries to force me to do anything.
And I would rather lose
everything I have than yield to
this pressure, because if you
submit to this pressure and agree
with something that is fundamentally
wrong and violates the rights
of other people as well,
you become broken inside. You
become a shell of your former self
on a deep biological and spiritual level.
So, I wouldn't do that. There are probably
other people in the world that would
consider that, but I don't care. Telegram
disappears, too. Something people don't
understand, including in these intelligence
services or governments. I don't
care. I'll be fine. If they put
me into prison for 20 years,
which, let's be clear, it's not something
that I think is realistic, but let's
just think about it as a
hypothetical situation,
I would rather starve myself to death
and die there, reboot the whole game,
than do something stupid.
- Let me ask you about an example of the thing
you're talking about. Tell the saga of
Telegram in the Romanian
election. So, amidst all
this, you are still fighting
to preserve the freedom of
speech. What happened, and what were
some of the decisions you had to make?
- So, when I got stuck in France, unable to
leave the country for a few months, I was
offered to meet the head of state foreign
intelligence services through a person I
know quite well. He's actually a
well-known tech entrepreneur in France,
and he's well-connected, and he
said, "This guy wants to meet you." I
said, "Okay, fine. Let's do that, but I'm
not promising anything." I
took the meeting, and in this
meeting, I was asked to restrict what
I see as restriction of freedom of
speech in Romania. I don't know if you
follow the whole saga with the Romanian
elections. They had presidential
elections last year.
The results were- got canceled.
Now, Romania, at that point when I
had this meeting, was preparing for
a new presidential election. The
conservative candidate was not somebody who
the French government was
supportive of, so they asked me
whether I would be shutting
down, or ready to shut down,
channels on Telegram that supported
the conservative candidate, or protest
against the pro-European
candidates, so they
called the guy they liked. I said, "Look,
if there is no violation of the
rules of Telegram, which are quite
clear, you can't call to
violence. But if it's a peaceful
demonstration, if it's a peaceful debate,
we can't do this. It would be political
censorship. We protected
freedom of speech in
many countries in the world,
including in Asia, in Eastern
Europe, in the Middle East. We're not
going to start engaging in censorship in
Europe, no matter who's asking
us." I was very clear to the guy who
was the head of French intelligence.
I said, "If you think that because I'm
stuck here, you can tell me what to
do, you're very wrong. I would
rather do the opposite every
time." And in a way, that's what I
did. I um... had a small debate with
him about the morality of this,
this whole thing, and then
at a certain point, just
disclosed the content of this
entire conversation, because I never
signed an NDA. I don't ever sign
NDAs with any people like that. I want to
be able to tell the world what's going on.
And that's quite shocking to me,
that you would have people in the French
government trying to get an advantage
of this situation. Of course,
if, you know, they had nothing
to do with the start of
this investigation itself,
and use it to reach their political
or geopolitical goals. I consider it
an attempt to humiliate
myself personally and
millions of Telegram users
collectively. And it's quite
strange that the same agency asked us to
do certain things in Moldova as well.
do certain things in Moldova as
well. So even before that, I
think it was October of
last year, or September. I
was arrested in Paris in late August,
and then again approached through an
intermediary, and asked, "Would you
mind taking down some channels in Moldova?
Because there is an election going on,
and we're afraid there's going to be
some interference with these elections.
Could you please connect with the
representatives of the government of Moldova
and take care of it?" We said, "We're
happy to take a look at it and see if
there is content there that is in violation
of our rules." And they sent us a list
rules." And they sent us a
list of channels and bots.
bots. Some of them were... So
it was a very short list, and
some of these channels and bots were
in violation indeed of our rules, and
we took them down, only a few of them.
The rest were okay. Then they said,
"Thank you," and sent us another list of
dozens of channels, many, many channels.
We looked at these channels, we realized
that there is no solid foundation
to justify banning them, and we
refused to do that. But interestingly
enough, the French intelligence services
that were asking us to do this in Moldova
let me know through their contact
that after Telegram banned
the few channels that were in
violation of our rules in
Moldova, they talked to my
judge, the investigative judge
in this investigation that is
started, is has been started against me,
and told the judge good things
about me, which I found very
confusing, and in a way shocking, because
these two matters have
nothing in common. Why would
anyone talk to an investigative judge that
is trying to find out whether Telegram
did a good enough job in
removing illegal content in France?
What does Moldova have to do with it?
I got very suspicious at that moment.
Remember, it happened after we
blocked a few channels that
violated our rules, but
before we refused to block a
long list of other channels
that were completely fine, which
is people expressing political
views, which I may not agree with,
but it's their right to express them.
Not extreme views, not views
that call to violence.
That was extremely alarming.
That was a moment when
I told myself that there may be more
going on here that I initially
thought. Initially, I thought,
"Yeah, some people are confused about
how technology works." And here,
after this case in Moldova,
I got much more suspicious. So by
the time the head of intelligence
services met me to ask about Romania,
to help them silencing conservative
voices in Romania, I was already
wary of what could be going on next.
- Yeah, so clearly this was a systematic
attempt to pressure you to censor
political voices that the French
government doesn't agree with. And we
should say that you have fought for
freedom of speech for left-wing groups
and right-wing groups, it really doesn't
matter. So it's not, you don't have a
political affiliation, political
ideology that you fight for. You're
creating a platform that, as long as
they don't call for violence, allows
people from all walks of life, from all
ideologies to speak their mind. That's the whole
point. And it happens to be
conservative voices in the Romanian
election that the French government
wanted to censor, because currently the
French government leans left. But
if you flip everything around
and the government would be
right-wing, you'd be fighting against
censorship of left-wing voices. And
you have in the past, many times.
- Exactly. Ironically, we
received a request from the
French police to take down a channel
of far-left protesters on Telegram
in France. We refused to do that. We looked
at the channel, peaceful protesters.
It doesn't matter for us whether we're
defending the freedom of speech of people
leaning right or leaning left.
During COVID, we were protecting
activists that were organizing
the Black Lives Matter
events, and the other side,
the protesters against
lockdowns. We protect
everybody as long as they are
not crossing the lines and not starting to
call to violence or
incite damage to public
property. It's a fundamental right
to assemble. It's interesting that
people who haven't had this
experience of living in countries
that don't have freedoms
don't always realize
how dangerous it is to
gradually compromise
your values, your principles,
your freedoms, your rights,
because they don't
understand what's at stake.
- Yeah, these things become a
slippery slope. So for many,
many years, including currently, you have
spoken very highly of France. You love
French history, French culture. I think
this situation, this historic wrong that's
been done is simply just
a gigantic PR mistake
for France. There's no
entrepreneur that aspires to
be the next Pavel Durov to create
the next Telegram, sees this
and wants to operate in France
after seeing this. There is
no justification for this arrest,
there's a misapplication of the law, all
kinds of pressures, all kinds of
behavior that seems politically motivated,
all that kind of stuff, all the excessive
regulation and bureaucracy. A
nightmare for entrepreneurs that
dream to create something impactful
and positive for the world. So what do
you think needs to be fixed about
the French government, the French
system? And then zooming out, because
you have seen similar kinds of things in
Europe that could enable
entrepreneurs, that could
reverse the trend that we
seem to be seeing in Europe
that is becoming less and less
friendly to entrepreneurs.
What can be fixed? What should be fixed?
- I think the European society must decide
where they want the ever-increasing
public sector to stop
increasing, what they think
should be the right size of government.
Because today, if you take France, for
example, which is a beautiful country
with a lot of talented people, but
public expenses are 58% of
the country's GDP. It's
maybe as much or more than in the
latest stage of the Soviet Union.
So you have this balance
where you have many more
people representing the state as opposed
to people trying to bring the country's
economy forward by creating great
products and great companies.
The startup field, in my field, social media
field, has been affected by it immensely.
There was one great startup in this realm
in France in the last 10 years. It was
a location-based social
network. It was eventually sold
to Snapchat, but before it was
sold, the founder asked me
whether he should sell. I told him, "Never
sell. You have a great thing
going. You have lots of users.
You have organic traction
in many countries."
And the first of this kind
of success story in France.
But then he sold anyway in a
couple weeks. And later, I met
him, he's trying to do a new thing
now. I met him and I asked him,
I was trying to understand what went wrong.
And one of the things he told me about
is that while he was trying to run his
company, you know, competing with Facebook,
Instagram, Snapchat, having
all this pressure from
investors, trying to hire the best
people and persuade them to go to Paris,
and he did a great job, by the way.
But while he was trying to do that,
he got also attacked by some silly
investigation, again involving data protection
issues, which lasted forever, and
was gradually sucking the blood of
his team and his company,
constant interrogations,
disclosure requests. And
this is a young company.
It significantly increases the
level of stress, and at some
point, I think the pressure was too much.
He decided, "I'm going to just sell
it." Eventually, it turned out that
there was no issue. The investigation
ended, as far as I understand,
with no charges. But such investigations,
they have a price, they have a
cost. And unless the
society realizes the cost
of projects, of companies, of startups
that are never created, or are sold to
the United States at the very early
stage, or other countries, resulting
in decreased economic growth,
things won't change. I think we
just talked to a guy a few days ago
who left France and started a business
here in Dubai, and one of the
reasons he had to leave France is that
the government started an investigation
on his company, and they froze his
bank accounts, and this investigation
that involved taxes lasted for many,
many years. I believe he said eight
years. And at the end of these eight
years, the government reached
the conclusion that there
was nothing wrong. "He's good.
It's okay." In the meantime,
his corporate bank accounts
were frozen. His business died.
The only reason why he was able
to retain sanity is because he
moved to Dubai and started a new
company, which is incredibly
successful, and now he's
enriching this city, which we're in right
now, with his great ideas and creativity.
- And by the way, having interacted
with him, there's like a
fire in his eyes, the
human spirit that fuels
entrepreneurship. Whatever that is, he
doesn't have to do. He's made a lot of
money. He probably doesn't have to do
anything, but he still wants to create.
And that fire's what fuels great
nations. Build, build, build,
build new stuff, expand, all of that,
and regulation suffocates that.
- You have to cherish those people.
But I guess the French public, or
some part of the French public, was
misled, and I don't know
when, perhaps since
the time of the French
Revolution, to believe
that entrepreneurs are somehow their
enemies. They're the evil rich people
that are the cause of all
problems, as if only you could
make the rich share their
ill-gotten wealth with the rest
of the population, then every
problem will be magically
solved. In reality though, a
lot of these people, that are
starting such companies with
fire in their eyes, are
sacrificing their lives, their
livelihood. They're working 20 hours
a day. They're experiencing immense
stress in order to fulfill their vision
and bring value and good to
the society around them. They
create jobs. They create great
services. They create great
goods. They make your country
grow. They make your people
proud. You have to cherish them. But
what does the system do to them? It
squeezes them out, because, perhaps there
was somebody in the tax authority that
decided to advance their career, and
perhaps, you know, was
too ambitious and not too
smart, so as a result, the company was
destroyed. And now the same
entrepreneur, by the way, who we
talked to, is invited to
come back to France. He's
being offered really good terms. He
said, "Are you gonna open this new
venue on the Champs-Élysées?
We're gonna give you the best
location. We're gonna fund
part of it, tax breaks."
And he said, "Never.
Just forget about it."
"It's impossible. I'm not
coming back to France."
He's traumatized by the experience,
and he's French. He was
born there. He has a French passport. So,
unless things like this
change, France will,
and the rest of Europe, will keep
struggling with economic growth,
with budget deficits, with unemployment,
and all the other relevant social and
economic metrics.
- Yeah, it's heartbreaking.
As many of these nations, I
appreciate the historic and the
cultural value, and I hope Europe
and France flourish, but these are
not the components required for
flourishing. Quick pause, I need a
bathroom break. All right, we had
some tea. We're back.
Let's go back a bunch of years to the
beginning. You mentioned you went
to school with a super intensive
education. So, I thought it'd be really
interesting to look at some of
the powerful aspects of that
education, from the languages
to the math. Can you actually
describe some of the rigorous aspects
of it and what you gained from it?
- At the age of 11, I got
the opportunity to enter
an experimental school in
St. Petersburg where I
lived, and we had to pass a
rigorous test to get accepted.
The idea behind the school was
that if you try to squeeze as
much information as possible
into a brain of a teenager,
making a focus on math and foreign
languages, then there will be
some changes in the brain
of the student that will
allow the student to understand most
other disciplines. But we had a
class as a result that didn't
have any single focus. It was
very widespread across
a lot of disciplines.
You would have at least four foreign
languages, including Latin, English, French,
German. In addition, you can get Ancient
Greek. You would have classes like
biochemistry or psychoanalysis, evolutionary
psychology. The difference of this class
as opposed to other classes in the
same school, which was part of the
Saint Petersburg State University
and called Academic Gymnasium, was that
unlike other classes, which
were specialized in some
single subject like physics or math
or history, this one tried to get
the best from all of these
specialized classes and bring it into
one curriculum. Since it was
an experimental class, it
wasn't possible to become a straight-A
student, to be excellent in all the
subjects. It was considered
crazy to even try.
- So just assume nobody's able to handle it,
you're just pushing the limits of the human
mind. Four languages in parallel, math,
evolutionary psychology, just overwhelming
the mind and see what happens.
- Yes, see what happens.
This was an experiment.
And it was in the middle of
the '90s, remember, when
Russia, particularly its
educational system, wasn't
regulated as much as it is today. It was
in the middle between the
two stages of the Russian
history, the Soviet's history
and the modern Russian history
of the 21st century. In any case, I learned
a lot from that experience. First of
all, why I got into this
course is because I kept being
kicked out from other schools.
- Challenging authority?
- I was good at all subjects, but not
behavior, you know. We had this
behavior grade in the
Soviet Union, in early
'90s. Perhaps they even
have it today, I'm not
sure. I was very bad at behavior. Always
challenging the teachers, always
pointing out their mistakes.
- By the way, that's not such a bad
thing, right? Like, if you were looking
back, there's some value to
that, right? For young people
to, maybe respectfully, but challenge
the authority, the wisdom of old, right?
- I think I was very lucky
to be able to do that
and to be able to get
away with it in the end.
Because normally if you keep
challenging authorities,
you just get kicked out of all
schools, and then you end up
nowhere. So I eventually
got into a school where
challenging teachers
was not fully okay, but
it was something that you could
do and then you would start a
debate with the teacher, and normally they
would allow you to express your point of
view, and then some objective truth
may come out of it as a result.
But at that point, I was
pretty bored with my life, you
know? Every teenager gets to a
point when they have this sort of
existential crisis. What's the point
of life? What am I even doing here?
At some point, I decided since
I have to go to school anyway,
I might as well try to do something
impossible and become the best
student and get an A, or what we
called five in the Russian system,
on every single subject. And
that kept me busy for a while.
It was incredibly difficult because
you didn't have enough time.
Even if you just studied all the time,
not doing anything else, you didn't have
any time left to prepare all the homework
tasks and get ready for
all the tests. So I
ended up using the breaks
between classes, but I got to
the result I wanted to get
to. I got the excellent
mark in every subject, and that
kept me happy for a while.
- What did you understand about
an effective education system from studying
foreign languages at the same time,
doing such a diversity? Like, if you were
to design an education system from scratch
for young people, especially in the
21st century, what would that look
like? You posted about the value of
mathematics as a foundation for everything.
- Yeah, I still think math is
essential. It's something that
shapes your brain. It teaches you to rely
on your logical thinking to split big
problems into smaller parts, put them in
the right sequence, solve them patiently,
trying again if it doesn't
work. And this is exactly the
same skill you need in programming,
in project management, and start it
when you start your own company.
And it's one of the few subjects
in school which encourages you to
develop your own thinking
as opposed to rely on
what other people have to say and just
repeating their opinions. That is extremely
valuable. And of course, once you're good
at math, you can apply it in physics, in
engineering, in coding. And
it's not surprising there that
most of the most successful tech founders
and CEOs are very good at math and coding
because ultimately, it's the same
mental skill that you rely on. But
back then in the school, I realized
something else as well: it's that
competition is really important. Competition
is key. This is what motivates a lot
of teenagers
when they're at school. And if you
remove competition out of the education
system, you will end up forcing kids
to start competing elsewhere, for
example, in video games.
It's a trend you see now in many
countries, including in the West,
when well-meaning authorities or
parents say, "We don't want our
kids to be too stressed. We don't want them
to feel anxiety. So let's just get rid
of all the public grading
system, all these
rankings of who won, who
lost. We don't want any
of that." And part of it is
justified, but as a result,
some kids lose interest. Yes, you
eliminate the losers, but you end
up eliminating the winners as well.
And then if you're overprotective of
the kids in that age, they grow up,
graduate schools or universities, and
they are still not prepared for real
life because real life is constant
competition for jobs, for promotions,
for customers, and it's more brutal.
What you have as a result is
high suicide rates, high
unemployment, all the
things and negative trends
you see now in many
countries which thought eliminating
competition from their education systems
was a good idea,
they still persist. They still think
competition's a bad thing. They try to
eliminate competition from their economy
as well to an extent, saying, "We're gonna
make sure the losers don't lose and
the winners don't get too much."
But as a result, they make
their entire systems less
competitive, their entire
economies. Some of them in Europe
are now struggling to keep
up with China, with South
Korea, with Singapore, with
Japan, and other places
where the education system was based on
ruthless competition. So this is a hard
choice any civilization has to make.
We support competition, understanding
that eventually it leads to
progress in science and technology
and abundance for society at large.
Or we remove competition thinking that
somehow we can shield the future generations
from the stress that
competition inevitably causes.
- Yeah, I mean, it's grounded in a good
instinct of compassion. You don't want people
who are, who suck at a thing to
feel pain, but it seems like
struggle is a part of life. Either
you do it early or you do it later.
And it's true, that's such a
good point that competition does
seem to be a really
powerful driver of skill
development, like you
mentioned, pursuing mastery.
There's something in human nature
that, especially for young
people, if you can compete at a thing,
you're gonna be really driven to
get good at that thing. If you can direct that
in the education system as China does, as
many, as many nations like you
mentioned do, then you're going to
develop a lot of brilliant people,
resilient people, people that
are ready to create epic
stuff in the world.
- I think there is a lot of evidence
proving that we are biologically
wired to compete and establish
our understanding of
what our qualities are and talents are
in relation to other people around us.
And this is one of the ways
society self-regulates.
- Speaking of competition,
your brother, Nikolai,
he's a mathematician, programmer, expert
in cryptography. He has won the IMO,
International Mathematics
Olympiad. He got gold medal three
times, ICPC Programming two times,
has two PhDs in mathematics.
And you have worked together for
many years, creating incredible
technologies that we've been talking
about. So what have you learned about
just life from your brother?
- Well, first of all, I must
say I learned pretty much
everything from my brother, everything I
know. Because when we used to be kids,
we slept in the same bedroom, like
beds a few feet away from each other.
and I kept bugging him with questions.
I would ask him about dinosaurs and
galaxies and black holes and Neanderthals,
everything I could think
of, and he was my Wikipedia
back in the time when we didn't
have internet access. He's a
unique prodigy kid,
probably one in a billion.
He started reading at the
age of three, I think, and
he pretty fast got so
advanced in math that
by the age of six, he could
already read really sophisticated
books on astronomy. Sometimes when
he did it in public places like
buses or metro, my mom was criticized
by people who were witnessing it.
They would tell her, "Why are you
mocking your own kid with this
serious book? It's obvious
the kid can't understand
everything there. It's too complicated.
Even we don't understand anything there.
There are some formulas."
And he was already
sucking in this knowledge.
He just has this thirst for
information. So, he was
the source of all kinds of
great facts, useful
things, inspiring things.
He taught me pretty much
everything I know. At the same
time, he is incredibly
modest and kind, and this is
something I think a lot of people
that think they're smart but not
genuinely intelligent, lack.
More often than not, people who are
truly intelligent, they're also kind
and compassionate.
- And he is that.
- Definitely.
- You actually have been staying out of the
public eye for the most part. You've done very
few interviews. You're pretty
low-key. But your brother is on
another level. He's been staying out
of the public eye. What's behind that?
- Part of it is his natural modesty.
He doesn't need to do it.
He doesn't feel this urge to
show off, brag about stuff.
I tried to avoid it as well, but at
a certain point, I realized that
me being too private, too secretive,
becomes a liability because it creates
this void, this emptiness that
people and organizations that don't like
Telegram very much are willing to fill
with inaccurate information, and
they're willing to spread narratives
about Telegram, which can result in
strange situations, some of
which we discussed earlier,
for example, this French investigation.
- Yeah. I've gotten to know you
more and more, and there's a deep
integrity to you that I
think is good to show to the
world. There's a lot of attack
vectors on user privacy, and I
think the most important, the last
wall of protection is the actual
people that are running the company.
So it's important to some degree for you
to be out there, showing your true self.
So we should say that also you didn't
mention, but you're a programmer
From an early age, you started
coding at 10. First things you
built were a video game at 11, and then
eventually 10 years later, at 21, you
programmed the initial versions of
VK single-handedly. Can you talk
to me about your programming
journey that led to the
creation of VK? What was the VK
stack? Was it PHP mostly? How did you
figure out how to program websites,
all of that?
- I wasn't interested in programming websites
at first. I didn't even have access to
the internet when I was 10
years old. But I liked video
games. I didn't have enough of them,
and the scarcity forced me to start
building them, more computer
games just to play myself.
It's actually an interesting thing that
we sometimes don't realize
it, but scarcity leads to
creativity, and one of the reasons
you have so many people who love to
code coming from the Soviet
Union or other places which
didn't have much access to modern
technology, and more importantly, modern
entertainment, is that perhaps we were not
so much distracted by all this abundance
of different entertainment options,
which is not to say it's bad to
have those options. It's just a fact
that we sometimes don't appreciate.
So I started to build computer games.
My brother would sometimes guide me. For
example, I would create this turn-based
strategy, of course two-dimensional. Back
then, three-dimensional was too much for
me. But it wasn't as slick in terms of
the scrolling FPS, frames per second,
parameter, and asked my
brother how to optimize it.
He would guide me, and
this kind of learning and
training really shaped my coding skills
when I was younger. Then I started to
create video games for
my classmates. When we
played, for example, tic-tac-toe
on an infinite field in
my class during the breaks, you know,
and not tic-tac-toe, the three in a row.
This was a bit five in a
row, and an infinite field.
This is a much more interesting game,
and it gets quite complicated
if you keep playing
it. My classmates used to
love it, and some of my
classmates were really smart,
you know, champions of math
Olympians, sons and daughters
of professors at the
university, and I decided, "No, I
want to win every single time."
I don't want to lose even a single time,
so how do I win? I need to practice
more. But how do I practice more?
I need an opponent stronger than
myself. So, I coded this
game so that I would
play against the computer,
and the computer would
calculate, I think, four moves
in advance to choose the optimal
strategy. That wasn't enough, four moves
in advance. I would still
win over it. If I tried to
calculate five or six, it was too
slow. So, I asked my brother, "Help
me out here." So, he made
this algorithm. Eventually, I
trained myself to win every single
time, even with the computer back
then. We didn't have modern CPUs
and I could still retain some
self-confidence. I would go back to school
during breaks, play with my classmates, and
soon people started to lose interest.
None of my classmates wanted
to play this game anymore. I killed the
game. There's no- So after that, when I
got into St. Petersburg State University,
it was quite boring just to
study because it was too easy.
So, I thought, "What can I do
there?" I created a website for the
students of my faculty first. I
organized the creation of digital
answers to all exams and a digitized
version of all lectures, which was
something very unique back then.
Remember, it was 25 years ago.
I would put together a
website where I would
publish all these materials, and
pretty soon it became super popular.
I opened a discussion forum
there. In a few years, I expanded
to the university with all of its other
departments, and then to other
universities. We ended up having
tens of thousands of users just as a
student support tool. We had all kinds of
social features there: friends lists, photo
albums, profiles, blogs, all of it. It was
quite successful, and after
I graduated the university,
one of my ex-classmates from the school
reached out to me after
reading about my successes in
a newspaper, the main
business newspaper of St.
Petersburg, and he asked me,
"Are you trying to build
a Russian Facebook?" I said, "I'm
not sure. What's Facebook?" So, we
met. He, since he graduated in American
university two years before that,
he showed me Facebook. I thought,
"Well, I kind of already have all of this
technology, but it's valuable to know
which elements I should get rid
of in order to scale this thing
and have millions of users." This is also
something people don't appreciate that
sometimes in order to move forward
and have more success, you have to
get rid of things, including technology.
Getting rid of features is super important.
- Simplify, both for
scaling and for making it
amenable to just growing the user
base where people get it immediately.
- Yes. Otherwise, it's just too
complicated for the new user. The
existing users will be happy.
They'll be praising you. They'll
be asking you to add more stuff to make it
even more complicated. So, it's easy to
lose track and get disoriented if you are
only relying on the feedback of existing
users. As a result, I started
the website called Vkontakte, or
VK. It means "in touch"
in Russian. Initially to
solve my own personal
problem, I graduated the
university that same year and I
wanted to be in touch, remain in
touch with my ex-classmates from the university and
other fellow students. And of course, as a 20-year-old,
other fellow students. And
of course, as a 20-year-old,
I wanted to meet other people,
including good-looking girls.
So, I started to build it
from scratch. For that one
I thought, "I'm not going to
use any third-party libraries,
modules because I want to make it as
efficient as possible." I was obsessing
over every line of code. But then how
do you start something that
large? Like, I didn't have any
prior experience of creating a project
of that scale, which would involve
everything. Before, I
would reuse some existing
solutions. Here, I wanted to build
from scratch, so I called my brother.
He was a postdoc student in Germany at the
time in the Max Planck
University, and I asked him,
"What should I start from?"
And he told me, "Just build
a module to authorize users." Just
not a way to log in, you know?
Not even to sign up, just to log in,
because you can pre-populate the
database with credentials and emails
and passwords. It doesn't really
matter, but once you see that you can
type in your password and email and
you're in, and it tells you "hello"
using your name. Then you will have a clear
understanding where to go from there.
- Yeah, I mean, that's true.
- That's one of the best advice
I've ever got in my life.
It worked perfectly, by the way. I
started to build it and before I knew it,
there on that website,
photo albums, private
messages. This guest book
we used to call "the wall"
back on VK and, I guess, in
the early days of Facebook,
we ended up building something
even more sophisticated
than Facebook at the time, with more
features. I had a girlfriend at
the time, I asked her, "We need to
somehow come up with a database
of all Russian schools and
universities and their departments and
subdivisions." She did a great job
trying to source all this information
online or sometimes writing
emails to universities saying,
"Which departments do you have
exactly at this point?
We need to know," or
reaching out to the
Department of Education,
both in Russia and then
in Ukraine, and then
eventually in Belarus, in Kazakhstan,
and other countries where VK ended up
to be the largest and most popular social
network. So we did a few things that were
quite unique at the time, and for the
first almost a year, I was the single
employee of the company. I was the
backend engineer, the frontend
engineer, the designer. I was
the customer support officer.
I was the marketing guy as well, coming
up with all the wordings
and the announcements,
coming up with competitions to promote
VK, which worked quite well. That
was an incredible experience that
gave me knowledge of every aspect
of a social networking platform.
- Also, an understanding of how
much a single person can do.
- Exactly. It's one of the reasons
why I like to think I'm an
efficient project manager and product
manager inside Telegram, because
I will not take anything but ambitious
deadlines from my team members. If somebody
gives me, "Oh, I need three weeks to
do that." I would reply, "Well, I
built the first version of VK in just
two weeks. Why would you need three
weeks? It seems like something you could
make real in just three days.
Three weeks? What are you
going to do the rest of the three
weeks apart from those three days?"
And, you know, the team
knows me, and that's why
we are able, today at Telegram,
to move at a very good
pace of innovation every
month. We're pushing
several meaningful features, I think,
out-competing everybody else in this
industry in terms of what you can do
within a short timeframe.
So yes, that experience was
invaluable. As for the
stack, I started from
PHP and MySQL, Debian
Linux, but very soon I
realized I needed to optimize
this. I started using
Memcached. Apache servers were not
enough anymore. We had to set up NGINX,
and my brother was still living in
Germany, so he couldn't help me much
for the first year of building VK.
Sometimes I would manage to get through
to him through a call. I would use an
old-school phone to call him with wires
and say, "What do I do? How do I install
this thing called NGINX? I'm not a
Linux guy." If he felt
particularly kind that day and not too
busy, he would show me the way to do it
or set it up himself, but for the most
part, I had to rely on just myself.
Having him there, though, helped when
we started to grow fast and scale
it, because at first
you realize, "Right now, one server is
not enough. I need to buy another one,
then another one and another
one. The database should
be in a different server. Then you have to
split the database into tables.
Then you have to come up with a
way to shard the tables using some
criteria that would make sense,
that wouldn't break your user
experience. When we got to over a million
users and beyond, a
dozen servers surviving
without the input from my
brother in terms of taking
care of the scaling aspect of it, became
impossible. I remember asking him to come
back. I said, "You need to help
me with this thing. It's starting
to be really big." What was worse is that
since we became popular,
somebody started to
do DDoS attacks on us,
as it always happens.
- Right.
- And then we had people that
wanted to buy a share of VK.
And interestingly, every time we had
a negotiation day, the DDoS attacks
intensified. So we had
to come up with a way to
fight it. I remember having many
sleepless nights trying to figure it out.
- So that was your introduction to
all kinds of bad actors, DDoS,
business. Then later you'd find out
there's such a thing called politics,
and then later geopolitics. But this is
the initial stages. That it's not just
about creating cool stuff.
It's having to deal with,
as you now have to deal with
with Telegram, is seas of bad
actors trying to test the limits of the
system, trying to break the system.
- Unfortunately, if we didn't
have bad actors and pressure,
it would be the best job
ever. You just get to create.
- Yeah. Yeah. And so the help from
your brother, like you mentioned, NGINX and
sharding the tables, some of the scaling
issue is algorithmic in nature. It's
almost like theoretical computer
science. So it's not just about, like,
buying more computers. It's figuring
out how to algorithmically make everything
work extremely fast. So some of it is
mathematics. Some of it is pure
engineering, but some of it is mathematics.
- Yeah, so at that stage I could
do the basic stuff. I could
understand how I implement scalability
into the codebase, how I sharded my tables
in the database, where I include
Memcached instead of direct
requests to the database.
That was quite easy
because it was still PHP back in
the day. When my brother got back
from Germany somewhere around 2008,
I asked him, "Can we make it even
more efficient? Can we make it
super fast, and at the same time
so that we would require even
fewer servers to maintain the load?"
And he said, "Yes, but, you know,
PHP is not enough. I'll have
to rewrite a big part of your
data engines in C and C++. I said,
"Okay, let's do that." He invited
a friend of his to help him, another
absolute champion in world's
programming contest
twice in a row, and they
they put together the first
customized data engine, which
was far more efficient than just relying
on MySQL and Memcached, because it
was, first of all, more
specialized, more low level.
- So they rewrote it in C, C++?
- A large chunk of it, like,
for example, the search, the
ad engine, because VK had
targeted ads. They built
that. It was, it was very efficient
what they did. Eventually
the private messaging part,
the public messages part.
At some point, we realized there are very
few websites online that load faster than
VK.
- Nice.
- I remember in 2009, I
went to Silicon Valley
and I met Mark Zuckerberg the first time
and some of the other core team members of,
of early Facebook.
Remember, Facebook was just
four or five years old then.
And everybody kept asking
me, "How come even here in
Silicon Valley, VK loads
faster than Facebook? Everything seems to
appear instantly on your
website. What's the secret
sauce?" It was one of the things
that made them very curious.
- And that was always important to you to have
very low latency to make sure the thing loads
and... because that's one of the things
Telegram is really known for. Even on
crappy connections and all that kind of stuff,
it just works extremely fast. Everything is
fast.
- It's one of the core technological
ideas. We prioritize
speed. We think that people can notice
the difference even if it's
just, like, 50 millisecond
difference. The difference is subconscious.
It also allows us not just to be faster
and more responsive, but also
more efficient when it comes to
the infrastructure, the expenses,
because if your code executes
faster, it means you need fewer
computational resources
to run it. So there is no
way you can lose in making things
faster, and that's why we have
always been very careful when hiring
people. I would only hire a person if
I'm ultimately certain it's the best
option. Because if you hire somebody who is
maybe a little bit distracted,
inexperienced, you may end up with
inefficiencies in your codebase
that results in tens of
millions of dollars of
losses. And think about the
responsibility. If we jump to today
from the VK days, Telegram is used by
over a billion people. They open
it dozens of times every day.
Imagine the app opens with
a slight delay, say half a
second delay. Multiply it by dozens
of times by a billion. It's...
centuries, millennia lost for
humanity without any reason
other than just being sloppy.
- That is so important to
understand and so wise,
that if you're just a little
bit careless as a developer,
you can introduce inefficiencies that
are going to be very difficult to track
down, because you don't know that
it can be faster. The code doesn't
scream at you, saying, "This could be
much faster." So you have to actually, as
a craftsman, be very careful
when you're writing the code
and always thinking, "Can this be done
much more efficiently?" And it can
be tiny things, because they
all propagate throughout the
code. And so there's a
real cost in having a
careless developer
anywhere in the company.
Because they can introduce that inefficiency,
and all the other developers won't
know. They'll just assume it kind
of has to be that way. And so
there's a real responsibility for every
single individual developer that's
building any component
of an app like Telegram
to just always ask, you
know, "Can this be done more
efficiently? Can this be
done more simply?" And
that's like one of the most beautiful
aspects, the art forms of programming, right?
- Oh, yes, because when
you manage to discover
a way to simplify things, make them more
efficient, you feel incredibly happy.
...and proud and accomplished.
And to your point, I
can recall a few instances
in my career when
firing an engineer actually
resulted in an increase in
productivity. Let's say you have 200
engineers building the app, and then
just... they just can't make
it. They're not keeping up with
the pace of the feature
release schedule, and
you think, "I probably have to
hire a third one." But then you
notice that one of them is really weird,
falling behind the schedule, complaining
some of the time, doesn't
assume responsibility.
And you ask, "So what if I just fire
this person?" And you fire this
person. In a few weeks, you realize you
actually don't need, I mean, you
never needed the third engineer.
The problem was this guy who created more
issues and more problems than he solved.
That is so counterintuitive
because, you know, in developing
tech projects we tend to think that
you just throw more people into
something and then things get solved
miraculously by themselves just because
more people means more
attention from them. No.
- That's, again, extremely powerful. The
you know, Steve Jobs talked about A
players and B players, and there's
something that happens when you have
B players, which is kind of like
the folks you're talking about,
introduced into a team. They can
somehow slow everybody down. They
demotivate everybody. And
it's very counterintuitive.
They basically... Part of the
work of creating a great team
is removing the B players.
It's not just hiring
more in generally speaking.
It's finding the A players,
quote unquote, and removing the
people that are slowing things down.
- Oh, yes, because the other thing
that people don't realize is how
demotivating working with a B player is.
Everybody can tell if the other person,
the other engineer they're working with
is really competent. And
it's very visible if
the person is not comfortable,
they're asking the wrong questions,
they keep lagging behind.
And at a certain point
if you're an A player, you get this
dissatisfaction, this feeling that you are not
able to realize your full
potential, accomplish what
you're really meant to accomplish
because of this person
working next to you or
pretending to work next to you.
And, by the way, in some cases
it's not because the person's
lazy. In some cases it's just, you
know, their mental, their intellectual
ability is not there. It's not about
experience. Most often it's about
natural ability and persistence. In 90%
of cases, it's just the inability to
focus on one task for an extended period
of time. Not everybody has this ability.
So for people who do have this ability,
it's an insult to work alongside someone
who is distracted and cannot go deep in
the projects that they're responsible for.
- What's on this small
tangent, what's your hiring
process? You've shown, you've talked about
how you use competitions often, coding
competitions, to hire, to find great
engineers. What- what's
your thinking behind that?
- Well, it's in line with
my overall philosophy. I
think competition leads to
progress. If you want to create
an ideal process to- for selecting the
most qualified people for certain specific
tasks you have in mind.
What can be better than a
competition? A coding contest where
everybody who wants to join your company
as an engineer, or just wants to get
some prize money or validation,
can demonstrate their skills,
and then we just select
the best. Or if we are not
certain because there's not enough data
to hire somebody, we just repeat
the contest with another task,
get more data, get more winners. Then
repeat again. At some point, you
realize, "Oh, actually, this guy
has competed in 10 of our contests since
he was 16 years old, or 14 year old.
Now he's 20 or 21. He
won in eight of these
competitions. He seems to be really good
in JavaScript, in Android Java, and also
C++. Why not hire this person?
There's some consistency there. And a lot
of these people, they have never worked in
a big company before, which is
priceless. Because in a big company,
people tend to shift responsibility.
They have this shared
responsibility wherein
nobody fully understands
who can take credit for a project,
who can take blame for a project.
Inside Telegram, it's pretty
clear, and these competitions are
the closest experience to what people
will have when working at Telegram.
So for example, we want to
implement some very tricky
animation and redesign to our
profile page of the Telegram
Android version. And the Android app, it's
an open-source app. Anybody can take its
code and play with it.
So as a result, we would
not just select the best
person and hire this
person, we would also select the best
solution to the problem, because we would
not suggest the contestants
to solve trivial
problems. It's something that's
valuable, it saves a lot of time
for us in terms of development.
And because I always
had these large social
media platforms which
I could use to promote
these competitions...
...somehow both VK and Telegram
were very popular among engineers
and designers, other tech people.
I had no issue to promote
this contest and find the
right people, ever. And
what can be better than
for an employee of your company,
somebody who has been a user of
it? If this person has no prior experience
of using Telegram, their
understanding would be very
limited. Why would I even try to
hire somebody from LinkedIn who
worked at Google and other companies, is
used to receiving a salary for nothing,
is used to shifting responsibility
and being stuck in endless meetings,
and has very limited understanding
of what Telegram stands for?
It's just crazy if you think about it.
- Yeah, and then because of that,
you're extremely selective and slow
in hiring. So the people really have to
earn their spot. And as a
result, I got a chance to sit in
one of the team meetings where
people discuss the different
features that are being developed, the
different ideas, some of which are at the very
cutting edge. So you get to see behind
the scenes how it's possible to
have such a fast rate of
idea generation. So you generate the
idea, you implement the prototype and
then eventually it becomes an actual
feature in the product. And so that's why
you have this kind of half-hilarious,
half-incredible fact that for
many as compared to WhatsApp and
Signal, you've led the way in many other
features. Many of the features we take
for granted now, many of which we know
and love, like the auto-delete timer.
That was seven years ahead of any
other messenger. Message editing,
replies, these are all
obvious things you...
I've even forgotten for some of
them that they were never part.
I mean, I think the auto-delete
timer is a really brilliant idea.
- We implemented it in 2013 in the secret
chats. The funny thing about it is
then when other apps started to copy
it, like WhatsApp seven years after,
and then Signal and some other apps,
they initially even copied the exact
timestamps. So for example, if we had like
one, three, and five seconds, they would
also have one, three, and five seconds.
They tried not to change it
because they were not sure
what was the magic sauce
behind the feature.
And ironically, it happens
with many of these things.
For example, when we design how you reply
to a message, and you have a small snippet
showing that you're replying to this
message and now you're typing your
response, then there is a small
snippet in the message itself
that, well, if you tap on it,
highlights the original message
you're replying to. Seems
pretty obvious. But there are
certain design decisions that we
were implementing at the time, and
we got this vertical line on
the left, and all these other
small things that are completely arbitrary,
right? You can do it in a different
way. But somehow, the
entire industry ended up
copying exactly that solution,
so now wherever you go,
WhatsApp, Instagram Direct,
Facebook Messenger, Signal, it
doesn't matter, you would see
exactly the same or pretty much
similar experience because nobody
really wants to take the risk
and innovate. If something
works, why not just copy it?
- Yeah, but we should say that it's done
extremely well. The vertical line and the
highlighting, I mean, all of these
are tiny little strokes of genius
by highlighting the text in a
certain way that, from a design
perspective, makes it very clear that
this part was written before
and the thing under it is your
reply. The distinction between the different
formatting of the text. I mean, there's
a... listen, I know how much typography is
an art form. There's a lot of interacting
graphic artistic elements inside Telegram
that all have to play together extremely
well. Like you pointed out to me,
there's this thing that just blew my
mind, which is the background gradient
of Telegram shifts. It changes
and it adjusts really nicely to the bubbles,
the chat bubbles, and then there's like
graphic elements on top of the gradient
that all interplay together. So
all of that has to work really
nicely without sacrificing
clarity. Everything is just
intuitive. That's very
difficult to create. That is art.
And on top of that, it's super fast.
- That's the hardest part. To make
it look so that designers love
it is one thing. The
real challenge is make
it look the way the designers
love it and make it
work on the weakest device
as possible, the oldest,
cheapest smartphones
you can imagine. So if
you take the moving gradient
on the background of
every Telegram chat, this
is something most people
don't notice, but they can feel it.
- Yeah, yeah. They notice it subconsciously
or something like that. There is a pleasant
feeling. There's a feeling,
there's a pleasant
feeling when you're
reading a chat and that's
where the design contributes
to that. I think a
gradient really does. I really
love that about Telegram, the
gradient. Not the technical thing you
described, but the feeling of it.
And then the technical aspect
of creating that feeling is
incredible. I could probably come
up with all kinds of algorithms of
rendering that gradient that's
going to be super inefficient.
And so doing that efficiently is like...
- Or efficient, but not
too beautiful, because-
- Right.
- ...even doing something so
trivial as a gradient can result
in noticeable lines in the gradient. The
person can instantly say, "Oh, no, it's
not the right thing." So you have to
introduce certain randomness there
and then you have the gradient, but it's
not enough. It's too plain. You want
to have certain pattern
as an overlay, but it
should be simple enough not to
distract you from the content,
but it has to be entertaining enough
to create a good feeling about
the whole app. And another
question, what kind of objects
you want to include in this pattern? And
how would this pattern work? Will it be
based on pixels or would it be
vector-based? And would it be vector-based
so they will be infinitely
scalable and high quality?
And then, I think for the
default pattern and the default
background, which is based on four
colors. It's not a gradient based on two
colors; it's four colors, and they're
constantly shifting. I probably looked through
several thousand variations of them
because this is such an important decision to make.
It's the default back. Of course, you can change
it. Actually, you can set up your own
four colors for that. You can change it.
- No way. Really?
- Yes. You can do it. And you
want to rely on certain
deeply hard-coded biological
properties of the
human mind, right? So
which color do you want to
use? Is it gonna be blue?
Is it gonna be yellow? Is
it going to be green?
Because each color has a
different meaning in our brain.
And what kind of objects
you want to put there. Something from
our childhood, something from
nature, or something that
can create a different kind of mood.
And this is just one detail of the
app. So there are many
details. When you send a
message, you are done typing a
message, and you then tap send
and then the message gradually appears in
the chat. How does it happen? So you want
the input field to slowly
morph into the actual message.
- To the message, yeah.
- And, and you want this to
be done regardless of the
contents of the message, because sometimes
the width would be different, sometimes it
would be containing media or a link
preview or other stuff that will change
the message bubble. So you go
through countless different
scenarios and make sure
every one of them works
great, even if this message contains
4,000 characters. And then you
look at all the platforms: iOS,
Android, and all the old devices
of all kinds of outdated operating systems
and the hardware and you cross the
two because you can have this really
bad old phone but using
the newest operating
system version, so what do you do?
What kind of bugs do you get there?
And then, of course, since
Telegram works on tablets as
well, and our iOS version
works on an iPad,
which I love a lot. You
have to understand that
everything can be really big, so it can
consume a lot of space on your screen.
and then it will trigger using more
computational resources to render it. So,
there are a lot of nuances to it, but as
long as you obsess over every small detail,
at least every detail that
really counts, you can get to a
user experience. If you're really
used to Telegram, if you've been a
regular user for at least a few weeks,
going back to any other messaging app feels
like a serious downgrade.
- Yeah, I mean, there are so many really
magical moments. Like, for example,
the way a message evaporates when you
delete it. That is a really pleasant
experience.
- Oh, yeah. And boy,
was it hard to make, particularly
on Android? This is this Thanos
snap effect, right? So,
the message is broken into
tens of thousands of particles
which go away like dust
in the wind. It looks great,
but it was so hard to make.
- probably one of my favorite GUI
graphical things. It's just art. It's
it's pure art. It's incredible. So,
it's good to hear that it's been
really thought over and thought through,
because it's extremely well done.
- No, you can't pull it off if you're not
going deep into this. And then you
don't want to distract people from
their communication with all this
additional information, so you want
them to be invisible in a way.
- They create the feeling, but
they don't create distraction.
- Yes, and in order to do that,
you have to overcome even more
challenges. For example,
you mentioned this deletion
effect: message evaporates.
If you do the animation,
if you show the animation first,
and then the message that
is preceding the deleted message
that is going after the just deleted
message moves closer to each other,
then it doesn't feel right. It feels
too long, too imposing. So, what you want
to do is you want the message to disappear
while the messages around it go closer
to each other to fill the resulting gap.
And then you imagine what that involves,
redrawing the entire screen. So, on top
of this very complicated animation,
you have to think about things
like which kind of messages were
there before it, after. That
just adds to complexity.
- And once again, on all kinds of devices,
all kinds of operating systems, all kinds
of tablets, phones, desktop, all of that.
- But, you know, once you accomplish
it, it gives you this immense
sense of pride because
nobody's doing this.
Nobody really cares. In a way, maybe they're
right not to care. Maybe nobody notices
this. But there is something
about it that feels
wrong when such things are neglected
because I understand that every
day, tens of millions of people around
the world are deleting messages.
What kind of experience do they get?
Is this an experience that maybe
even subconsciously inspires them
and makes their heart
sing even a little bit,
fills them with joy, lightens up their
mood even a little bit by 0.001%?
Or is it something that is just
basic? And I think if we can
bring some value into
people's lives, even through
these subtle details, we have to
definitely invest our time in it.
- And some joy, not just sort of
value, value like productivity, but
joy. I think Steve Jobs, Jony Ive
talked about this. They would
put so much love and effort
into the design of everything,
including things that weren't visible
in the initial PCs, personal computers,
because they believe that somehow through
osmosis, the users will be
able to feel the love that the
designers put into the thing, and
you're absolutely right. I mean,
it's not about deleting
messages. I feel a little
inkling of joy when I see that
evaporation animation. It's just nice.
I'm happier because of it, and
so I feel that effort, and I
think, you know, a
billion users feel that.
- People like when other people care.
- Yeah. Yeah. That's exactly what it
is. And of course, there are the
more sexy things like all the
emojis and the stickers, the GIFs. Many
of those are just little art pieces.
- That's, again, an intersection of art
and technology because you look at the
stickers, which Telegram launched
way before most of these other apps.
- Three years and eight months ahead.
- Ahead of WhatsApp, yes.
But the stickers that WhatsApp
ended up launching three years and
eight months after, the
first version was not really
good because they just did regular
GIFs or WebM videos, which were
not based on vector graphics.
What we did is vector animations.
Each of these stickers is only
several kilobytes, sometimes maybe
a maximum of 20, 30 kilobytes
in size. But it's 180 frames. We were
able to run them at 60 frames per
second on all devices. And it's also very
challenging. It was a challenging
thing to do. We had so much headache
trying to make it work. Nobody even
tried to do anything like this
before us because it's crazily difficult.
But as a result, you have these fluid
animations, you have this really
nice user experience. Somebody sends
you a sticker, you don't have to wait for
it to load because it's so lightweight
and it starts moving instantly.
And then of course, it's not just
engineering. You have to find designers
that are able to create the stickers
using vector graphics, which
means they're based on
curves described by
formulas, not just created
as photographs with pixels.
Where do you find these
people? Again, we did competitions but
it was not easy to assemble a team
of artists, slash engineers, I would
say, that are able to do something like
engineers I would say that
are able to do something like
this. This is a unique form of
art. And this allowed us to
do a revolution in stickers,
then another revolution
in animated emoji that you
can add into messages,
custom animated emoji. I don't think
anybody did that. I think Telegram is
still the only one allowing
users to do that because you can
include a hundred of
animated emoji in a message
and they will be animated and they will
be moving and your device won't crash.
It's probably unnecessary and crazy
but we think somewhere in this
intersection of art and engineering true
quality is created and then
of course more recently
we expanded into what
we call Telegram GeMs.
which are essentially blockchain
based collectibles that
you can demonstrate on your
Telegram profile so that they
get social relevance but you can
also use them to congratulate your
friends and close ones with their
birthdays and other holidays
and that was received extremely well.
- Yeah, they can hold value, they can increase in value,
you could trade them for that in that aspect, but
to me, still the... The vector graphics,
and it's not just simple graphics, it's
incredibly intricate graphics
so the vector makes it very
efficient but it also allows you to
create, maybe it incentivizes the artist,
enables them, incentivizes them to
create super detailed intricate
elements and then the final result like you
would think it wouldn't matter but the final
result has like a lot of stuff going
on and it's, and it allows you to
scale on arbitrary devices
and not, now it's like this
little... you know like usually GIFs
from like back in the day and still in
meme form are low resolution and so
usually people don't put details and
intricate art into it but here
with vector graphics it's
like, like a million things going on and
it allows you to play with different
animations like you showed me
this thing where you send and you
hold for a while on the send button and so
you can share with the person
you sent a message to this
animation that you've encoded. Like there's
a bunch of stuff going on when they read the
message.
- Yes, we have a lot of features
like that when we use
this art to allow people
to express themselves.
and most people don't even
know about these features.
- I didn't know about it. That
was cool. That was cool.
- The other application of the
same technology is reactions on
Telegram because we made it
a goal to make sure that
people feel joy when they just send
you a like. Something so trivial
as just adding a like to a message
should be an action that you
want to perform again and again and again.
- So another feature is on the more serious
side is end-to-end encryption. So
you led the industry in that. It was
launched one year and three
months ahead. Can you speak
to why you decided to add
end-to-end encryption, how you
developed the current encryption algorithm in
the beginning? What was your thinking behind
that?
- So in 2013 when we were
launching Telegram,
we were aware of the
serious issue with privacy
that Edward Snowden made very clear.
And we thought, yes, we are designing
this product in a way that is
already extremely secure,
but we want to make
sure that not even we can
access user messages.
And we understood very clearly
that a bunch of people who
were born in Russia don't
necessarily inspire trust.
So that's why we made Telegram open
source. So all our apps have been
open available on GitHub since 2013.
And then we added end-to-end encryption in
our secret chats, which WhatsApp copied
a few years after. One year and three
months ahead, they just started to test
it. They rolled it out
I think 2016, which is
three years after us, and the only
reason I think the rest of the industry
had to do it is because
we set the standard.
It was incredibly important back in the
day, and at the same time, we realized
certain limitations of end-to-end
encryption. So within that
design, that architecture,
you can't support
very large chat communities
with consistent, persistent
chat histories. You can't support huge
one-on-many channels. You'd have issues with
maintaining bots that have
lots of incoming messages.
Multiple device support
becomes tricky. People
will end up losing some of the
documents they share, so we
also saw a lot of issues, and
we ended up having this sort of
hybrid experience, where
depending on your use case
and your requirements, you can choose the
level of encryption that we want to have.
- So that's why you chose to go
opt-in for end-to-end encryption.
So the trade-off there that
you're describing is between, for
people who really care about
specific messages extreme privacy on
those messages, and
usability, like being able to
sync across multiple devices,
having groups that are 200,000
people. So all of those features,
that quality of life features,
there's a trade-off between
those and end-to-end
encryption. So you lean towards
letting users sort of enable
end-to-end encryption for cases when
they want to be super secure.
- Yes, and Secret Chats are not just end-to-end
encrypted, you know. There are certain
limitations that are both their
feature and a bug. For example, you
can't screenshot them. You can't
forward any document, any message from
them, which is not necessarily
something you need when you're
trying to get some work
done and you're just
communicating with your team on a project.
So it became very clear to us that there
are different needs here, and if you try
to combine both in one type of chat,
you will end up losing a lot of utility.
You know, we at Telegram, we don't use any
collaboration tool for
teamwork. We use Telegram to
build Telegram. So we felt instantly
when we were trying to switch to, say,
Secret Chats to share large documents and
try to get work done, it was just not
adapted for it. At the same time, if you
were really paranoid, you think,
you know, "I don't wanna be
screenshotted, I don't
wanna have any leaks,
I don't even trust Telegram; I only trust
code," Secret Chats are the best option. I
believe it is the most secure
means of communication today.
- And we should say that there's a lot of
other aspects to this that are important.
For example, Telegram is the
only app that has open source
reproducible builds for both Android
and iOS. Why is this important?
- So, you need reproducible builds
in order to verify that the app
really does what it claims,
really encrypts data
in a way that it is described on its website.
For that, you need to make your apps
open source for any researchers
to have a look at it.
So, Telegram has been open
source since 2013. Apps like
WhatsApp have never been open source, so you
don't really know what they're doing and
how exactly they encrypt your
messages. What's important here,
though, is to understand whether the version
of the app that you download from the
app store corresponds exactly
to the source code that you can view on
GitHub. And for that, you need reproducible
builds. As you said, Telegram is the only
popular messaging app that does that.
We allow people to make
sure both on Android and
iOS that the source code of Telegram on
GitHub and the app you're
actually using is the same app.
I think it's incredibly important, not
just to gain people's trust, but just
to stay transparent and open
about it. When I make this claim
that Telegram's Secret
Chats are the most secure
way of communicating, I
really mean it, because I
haven't seen any fact contradicting this
claim. At least among the popular
messaging apps, you say WhatsApp,
Signal, iMessage, none of them have
reproducible builds on both iOS and Android.
None of them have, at least at the
same level, put so much effort
into making sure that
the algorithms that you
use in order to encrypt data are not
algorithms that have been handed to you
by some agency in order
to create a honeypot.
At least from what I know
about our competitors,
I don't think they went
through the same process.
- So, we should say that the entirety of the
software stack in Telegram is done from
scratch internally to Telegram, so we're
talking about not just the encryption
but everything running on the servers.
So the servers are built out, the
hardware and the software are all done
internally, which is one of the
ways you reduce the attack surface
on the entire stack that
handles the messages.
- It does make it more secure,
because if Snowden's revelations
taught us anything, is that very
often open source tools, modules,
libraries that are used by everybody
ended up having certain
flaws and security issues.
that make software
vulnerable. It's also a way
to make sure you're doing things
the most efficient way possible.
But it's extremely difficult to
do that. You really have to have
exceptional talent on
your team to achieve this
level of thoroughness, to go to a low
level of coding that allows you to
recreate from scratch database engines,
web servers, entire programming languages.
Because the programming
language we use on the backend
to develop the API for the client apps
is also entirely built by our team.
- Yeah, so minimizing reliance on open
source libraries is extremely difficult,
as most companies, they rely
on open source libraries.
- Well, I wouldn't say we're
completely independent from that.
We use Linux on the backend. There's no
way of avoiding it for us at the moment.
But for the most part, we are much more
self-reliant than most other apps.
- You mentioned Edward Snowden. A long time
ago, you wanted to work together with him,
perhaps to share expertise to
understand the full realm of this...
of what it takes to achieve cybersecurity.
What do you make of his case? What
lessons do you learn from
what he has uncovered, and
maybe even broadly, what impact has his
work had on the world, do you think?
- Well, the main lesson is not everything
is what it seems. As you would
discover, and this is
something that I found quite shocking
at the time, that a lot of people
who you thought were security
and cryptography experts
ended up being agents of the
NSA in one way or the other,
promoting flawed encryption standards.
You would end up discovering that
your government that was supposed to be
limited in how it can surveil its people
actually doesn't consider itself
that limited. And that was very
valuable for the world to understand.
I guess it also can be a
lesson demonstrating that we
humans don't get the balance
right. So 9/11 created
a situation when the government
had to respond, and it
responded, but it overreacted. It ended
up eroding certain basic rights and
freedoms, including the right to
privacy, because the
government always wants to
increase its powers, and
the government always
tries to do it at the expense
of citizens. You have
this situation when the cure is worse
than the disease. And I think it was
incredibly brave to do what Edward
did. I didn't get to work with him
or ever see him in person. We keep
in touch, we sometimes communicate,
but we're not close. I still
think what he did is laudable.
I hope someday we'll meet.
- You yourself have faced the full force
of various governments, intelligence
agencies.
Is there any intelligence agency you're
afraid of? Any government you're afraid of?
- I think they should all be equally
afraid of, or equally not afraid
of in a way. It's not that this
intelligence service can kill you
and the other can't kill you.
- They all can kill you?
- I guess they all can kill me
one way or the other, but
it's a matter of whether
I'm afraid of death.
- This goes back to the beginning of our
conversation, I think, multiple times.
So you're in general fearless
in the face of the pressure.
- That would be a very bold statement,
but I proved to be quite stress
resilient. And it's not
that you don't have
fear. You can have fear,
but you overcome this fear.
I don't think there is anything
at this point that can happen
to change the way I am.
- So you went through a
lot from 2011 to 2014,
government pressure that you
refused to give in to that led
you to create Telegram and let
go of VK. And then in 2018,
Russia and Iran decided to ban
Telegram. That was another
example of pressure. Can you take
me through that saga in 2018?
- So in 2018, Telegram started to become
popular. I think we had something like
200 million users, and it increasingly became
popular in places like Iran and Russia,
and other countries where sometimes people
have something to hide from the government.
In Iran, people used Telegram to protest
against the government. They
had these huge channels
that would use to organize the protests,
and eventually the government couldn't
keep up. They decided to ban Telegram.
People would still keep
using it, though, using
VPNs. It didn't help. The government
invested a lot in coming up with their own
messaging app. They had several teams
competing for the title
of the national Iranian
messaging app. All these
apps failed. People
still preferred Telegram. Interestingly,
Iran banned Telegram, but
WhatsApp wasn't banned, or at
least they unbanned WhatsApp soon
after. At the same time, starting
in mid-2017 or late-2017, Russia
demanded that Telegram hand them the
encryption keys. They thought
these things exist, something
that would allow them to
read messages of every
person on Telegram, or at least
every person on Telegram in Russia.
And we told them, "That's impossible.
If you have to ban us, ban us."
And this is what they ended
up doing in spring 2018.
And that was quite fun because they were
trying to block our IP addresses,
but we were prepared for that,
and we came up with this
technology that allowed us to
rotate IP addresses, replacing them with
new ones every time the censor blocks our
existing addresses. And then it
was completely automated. We had
millions of IP addresses. We would be burning
through them. We set up this movement
called digital resistance when
system administrators and engineers
all around the world, both inside and
outside Russia, could set up their own
proxy servers and their own IP
addresses for Telegram to rely
on in order to bypass censorship. We
ended up spending, I think,
millions of dollars on that.
And as a result, the censor got crazy there.
They would ban IP addresses and larger
subnets of IP addresses then. Huge
subnets which resulted in a weird
situation where parts of the
country's infrastructure started to
Like people were trying to pay for
groceries in the supermarkets, and
nothing would work
because the Russian censor blocked too
many IP addresses. And some of the
subnets were used to host other
unrelated services. Even some Russian
social networks and media
got affected, banks.
So they had to start being more
selective in how they combat
our anti-censorship tools. The biggest
resistance we got at the time was from
Apple. Apple didn't allow us to update
Telegram in their App Store, saying
for at least four weeks that we
have to come to an agreement
with Russia first. We said,
"It's not possible." They said, "We
will allow you to push your update
for Telegram worldwide, except for
Russia." We didn't want to do that.
Almost lost hope. You know, at some
point I said, "You know, maybe
this is the only way. Maybe we should
leave the Russian market. Stop
allowing users from Russia to download
the app from the App Store, which would
mean it's over." We helped organize
certain protests in defense of Telegram
and privacy and freedom of
speech in 2018 in Moscow.
There were hilarious people
flying paper airplanes.
- I saw that.
- And at some point, I decided, "I
have to make a statement. I have to
say that Apple sided with the censor."
That we are trying to do the right thing
here, but without Apple we can't do much,
'cause people can't
download your app anymore.
I published it in my channel and then
the New York Times picked it up with the
picture of the protestors flying paper
airplanes. Apple was criticized in that story,
and I thought, "Well,
Apple should probably
come back to the right side of
history here." And I waited for
one day and two days. In the
meantime, since we've been unable to
update Telegram for more than a month,
it started to fall apart because
the new version of iOS came out,
and it made the old versions of Telegram
obsolete. Some features that used to
work stopped working and users all
over the world started to suffer.
Like, people that had nothing to do with
Russia from other parts of the world,
experienced issues with Telegram.
So it was really serious, and I
said to my team, "You know what? If
by 6:00 PM today," I
think it was a Friday,
"nothing changes and Apple
doesn't allow us to push
the version of Telegram through,
let's just forget about the
Russian market. Let's keep going
because the rest of the world is more
important." It's sad, but what can we do?
- Which, by the way, removes all the people
that want to protest, all the people that
want to talk in Russia, it removes
their ability to have a voice
in the most popular messaging
app in that part of the world.
- Yes. Magically, 15 minutes to the time
I was planning to remove Telegram from
the Russian App Store in order to
proceed globally, Apple reached
out to us and said, "It's okay.
Your update is approved."
And we managed to keep playing.
this hide and seek game with the censor,
bypassing censorship through digital
resistance. In Iran, it was a little
bit different because we realized
it would've been too expensive to try to
come up with all those IP
addresses. And in addition, it was
not clear whether we wouldn't be in
violation of the sanctions regime,
so we did something else. We
created an economic incentive
for people who would set up
proxy servers for Telegram.
Any person, say an Iranian engineer, could
come up with a proxy server, distribute
its address among users in Iran, and
whoever connected through the proxy of this
person would be able to
see a pinned chat, an ad
placed there by the system
administrator, the owner of the
proxy. And this is how you can monetize
your proxy, so it created this
market, which resulted in Iranians
fixing their own problem
and as a result, we kept
millions, or maybe tens
of millions, of Iranian
users. Up until this day, I think
Telegram is still banned in Iran
today, but we probably have
something like 50 million people
relying on Telegram from that country.
- So the people find a way around?
- People find a way around.
- That's ingenious. That's
really great to hear.
I have to ask you about this.
After having spent many days with
you, I learned of something
that you've never talked about
at the time, have not
talked about to this day,
that there was an assassination attempt on
you using what appears to be poisoning in
2018. I think to me, it showed the
seriousness of this fight to uphold the
freedom of speech for everyone, for
all people of Earth that you're
doing. I have to say, it would mean a
lot to me if you tell me this story.
- Well, this is something I never talked
about publicly because I didn't
want people to freak out, particularly
at the time. It was spring 2018.
We were trying to raise funds for
TON, a blockchain project, working with
all kinds of VCs and investors. In the
meantime, we had a couple of
countries trying to ban Telegram, so
it wasn't exactly the best
moment for me to start
sharing anything related
to my personal health. But
that was something that is hard to forget.
I never felt ill. I believe I have perfect
health. I very rarely have headaches
or bad cough. I don't take pills
because I don't have to take pills,
and that was the only instant
in my life when I think I was
dying. I came back home, opened
the door of my townhouse, the place
I rented. I had this weird neighbor
and he left something for
me there around the door.
And one hour after, when I was already
in my bed, so I was living alone,
I felt very bad. I felt pain all
over my body. I tried to get up and
go to the bathroom. But
while I was going there,
I felt that functions of my body
started to switch off. First, the
eyesight and hearing, then I had
difficulty breathing, everything
accompanied by very acute pain,
heart, stomach, all blood vessels.
It was... It's a difficult
thing to explain,
but one thing I was certain
about is, yeah, this is it.
- You thought you were gonna die?
- Yeah. This is it, because I couldn't
breathe, I couldn't see anything.
It was very painful. I think it's over.
I thought, well, I have had a good
life. I managed to accomplish a
few... accomplish a few things.
And then I collapsed on the
floor, but I don't remember it,
because the pain covered
everything. I found myself
on the floor next day.
It was already bright.
And I couldn't stand up. I was
super weak. I looked at my
arms and my body, blood vessels
were broken all over my
body. Something like this
never happened to me. I
couldn't walk for two weeks
after. I stayed at my place,
and I decided not to tell most
of my team about it, because,
you know, I didn't want them to worry.
But it was tough. That was tough.
- Did that make you afraid of
the road you were walking?
Meaning all the governments, all
the intelligence agencies, all
the people. Like we mentioned,
it's like you're playing a video
game. You started with VK
where you're just trying to
build a thing that scales and all
of a sudden you find out there's
DDoS attacks attacking the security,
the integrity of the infrastructure,
and then you realize there's
politics, and then you
realize there's geopolitics,
and all of these forces are
interested in controlling channels of
communication, and you're just a curious
guy who created a platform for everybody
on Earth to talk, and all
of a sudden you realize
there's a lot of people attacking you.
How did that change your view? Did that
make you more scared of the world?
- Interestingly, not at all. If anything,
I felt even more free after that.
It wasn't the first time I
thought I was going to die. I had
an experience when I assumed
something bad is going to happen
to me a few years before that,
also in relation to my work. But,
you know, after you survive something
like this, you feel like you're living on
bonus time, so in a way,
you died a long time ago,
and every new day you get is a gift.
- As a bonus.
- Yes.
- And the first time you're referring to,
is that... would that have to do with
the complexity that was
happening with the pressure
from the government on VK? And
then you had to figure out
the increasing pressure and you
had to figure out what to do, and
you understood that you're losing
control of VK at that moment?
- The first of these instances
was in December 2011.
In December 2011, you had this huge
protest on the streets of Moscow.
They didn't trust in the
integrity of the election results
to the State Duma in Russia. I
remember in 2011, I still lived
in Russia, running VK.
There was no Telegram.
So the government demanded
that we take down
the opposition groups of
Navalny from VK that had
hundreds of thousands of members and
that were used to organize this protest,
and I very publicly refused to do that.
I just, you know, decided it's
not the right thing to do.
People have the right to assemble, and
I mocked the prosecutor who handed me
that demand and put out a scan of it,
and next to it, a photo of a dog
in a hoodie with its tongue out,
and I said, "This is my official
response to the prosecutor's request to
ban opposition groups." That was very
funny at the moment, but then I had armed
policemen trying to get into my apartment,
and I thought about many things
at that moment. I asked myself,
"Did I make the right choice?" And I came
to the conclusion that I made the right
choice, and I asked myself,
"What would be the next thing
that would logically follow from this?"
And I realized, "They're probably going to
put me in prison." So what am I
going to do about it? I asked
myself. And I told myself,
"I'm going to starve
myself, starve to death."
It's something that
probably many men have.
They're ready to die for
other people or certain principles they
strongly believe in. I'm not alone here.
I guess Edward Snowden was ready to die as
well, or some other people like Assange.
Also, at that moment, I realized there
is no way to communicate securely.
I need to tell my brother what's going
on. They're probably going after him.
How do I tell him without
betraying him? Because in
2011, remember, WhatsApp was already
there. I think they launched it in
2009, but it had zero encryption.
All messages were plaintext
in transit, meaning that even your
system administrator, let alone your
carrier, had access to your messages.
It was only after Telegram started this
push for encryption that these other apps
suddenly remembered that
privacy was in their DNA,
as WhatsApp founders famously stated,
but it must have been a dormant gene.
in 2011. So in 2011, there was no way...
to send a message in a
secure way. And I also told
myself, "If I'm going to
survive this, I'm definitely
launching a secure messaging app." Somehow
it ended up not being too bad. I
was summoned to the prosecutor,
answered some silly questions, fewer
questions that I had to answer
more recently in the
French investigation case.
But it was the beginning of
the end. It was clear that
there's no way I'm going to be allowed
to run VK the way I wanted it to run.
That was the moment I packed my backpack
and just started to
wait. I moved to a hotel
and realized any day I can
leave the country. I kept
running VK. I started to design Telegram
and assembling the team, but I knew
my days in Russia were numbered.
- Well, first, I really
have to say for myself,
millions, maybe hundreds of millions,
maybe the entirety of Earth, thank you
for putting your life on the line in those cases.
I think freedom of speech is fundamental to
the flourishing of humanity,
so. And it depends on people
willing to put everything on the line
for their principles. So, thank you.
Quick pause. I need a bathroom break.
All right. We're back, and once
again, we had a super long day,
and the fact that you would
spend many hours with me,
thank you for powering
through. We got this. It's
already late at night.
- Thanks for doing this.
- Okay. So there is increasing indication,
I think, from things I've seen
online that Russia is
considering banning Telegram.
First of all, do you think this might happen?
And what effect do you think this might
have on humanity? And, in general,
what do you think about this?
- It can definitely happen. As you said,
there are certain indications. There have
been certain test attempts to partially
ban it. Telegram is no longer
accessible in parts of Russia, such as
Dagestan. It would be incredibly sad
if Russia restores its attempts to
ban Telegram, because currently it's being used
by its population for all kinds of purposes,
not just personal communication or economic
business activities. But also, it's
communication or economic business
activities. But also, it's
the only platform which allows the Russian people
to access independent sources of information.
If you think about media outlets such as BBC or
any other non-Russian sources of information,
they're only accessible in Russia through
Telegram in the form of Telegram channels.
The websites are banned. Some other social
media sites are banned. And as you said,
like, there are indications that Russia is
planning to migrate users from existing
messaging apps such as WhatsApp and Telegram
to their own homegrown tool,
which would, of course, be fully
transparent to the government
and wouldn't allow voices independent from
the government to express themselves.
It's certainly an alarming trend. We see these
attempts in countries that are not famous for
countries that are not famous for
protecting freedom of speech, but
also increasingly in countries that
have been known to protect
freedoms. And this creates this
vicious circle, because in a way
European countries trying
to fight freedom of speech
under pretext that sound
legitimate, such as combating
misinformation or election
interference. They create precedents,
and they legitimize restrictions to
freedom of speech, which then, in turn,
can be used by authoritarian
regimes. And they would say,
in places like China or Iran that
they're not doing anything different.
It's the norm now to restrict voices that
that don't go in line with
the mainstream narrative.
That's sad, because one
of the things that makes
our life interesting is
this abundance of different
viewpoints, of different people that
we get to experience. You limit the
freedom of people, you
inevitably decelerate
economic growth, level of
happiness, the way people
can contribute to society,
the way people can express
themselves. I personally think
it would be a huge mistake
to ban a tool like Telegram
in any country, particularly a large
country such as Russia, because
the Russian people are incredibly talented
and resilient people. They are among the
first to start utilizing some of these
recent innovations that Telegram
implements. They are the early
adopters. I'd say them and
also the Americans, perhaps other people
from Eastern Europe like Ukrainians
and Southeast Asians. They're
among the first people to start
using any new addition that we launch.
They're incredibly hungry for innovation.
- So all that said there's
as part of the propaganda, and in general,
there's attacks on you all over the place.
There's misinformation. I've
read a bunch of things that
are, I think, in a systematic way,
lying about you, lying about Telegram
from all angles. Why do you get
attacked so much by everybody?
- Well, protecting freedom of speech is
not a way to make a lot of friends.
Because you would inevitably find
yourself in a situation where
you would be protecting the freedom of the
opposition to the current
government in any country
to express themselves. And then
the initial reaction and a very
basic, instinctive reaction of any government
would be to say, "Oh, our opposition
shouldn't be trusted and allowed to
express themselves, because they're
actually agents of some foreign
rival, a geopolitical force
that wants to destroy our
country." This is something that every
authoritarian regime in history used. You take
Stalinist Russia or Nazi
Germany, Maoist China. They'd
always use the same trick. They'd say,
"We need to limit your freedom of speech,
because these people who are
masquerading as opposition are
actually the agents of this
other country that wants to take
over. That's why, dear
citizens, forget about your
freedoms." And now increasingly,
you see similar attempts in
free countries. The initial instinct
from, say, President Macron's team
when they're confronted with some footage,
for example, the footage of his wife
slapping him, would be to say it's all fake
Russian imagery, something that is
inaccurate, something that is misinformation
or interference. And then when they are
confronted with more information, they
have to refine the narrative. So when
you find yourself in a situation
that you're running this platform
like Telegram, and then you
protect the freedom to express
ideas that don't go in line with the
mainstream narrative, you often find yourself
in this crossfire when the
forces in power will say that
you must be working with some
foreign government that they don't
like. Inevitably they would say that.
"Oh, if you're protecting
these voices, it's not right."
They love you when you're protecting
the freedom of speech in a country
that is far from them, or
better yet, in a country
that is their geopolitical rival.
They praise you for that, but
then they have this bipolar attitude
when you do the same in their own
country. And they say, "No, no, no,
no, no. We loved you for protecting
freedom of speech, but not here.
Not in my backyard. We don't
need it here. We're all
right. We have free press." And then you
will find yourself in this weird spot and
Ukrainians say you work for the Russians,
the Russians say you work for the
Ukrainians. And all this schizophrenia
is something that we had to deal with
for some time, because it's a
very easy way to attack you. At
some point you don't understand
where it is coming from. Is it our
competitors? And we must give
credit to our competitors if
it's their invention to launch
these kind of rumors, because
at a certain point they must have realized
they can't compete technologically
on the product side, so they
must do something like this. Or
it's just governments launching these
rumors, trying to discredit the
platform, trying to scare
their citizens away from
it, because they understand that their
power and grip over their own country is in
danger, as long as they allow a
pro-freedom platform to operate.
- And through all of this, we should
say over and over that you are
simply preserving the
freedom of speech for all
people of Earth, no
matter what they believe,
as long as they don't call for
violence and as long as they're not
doing some of the criminal activity
that we discussed, including terrorist
organizing. But other than that, it doesn't
matter what their belief, left wing or right
wing. You're just preserving their freedom of
speech. You think people of Ukraine, people of
Russia, and people of Iran, people
of all over the world understand
that, despite the propaganda against you?
- I think people are
smart. Every time I meet
somebody from one of these countries
you mentioned, in real life, people
recognize me in the street. Say here
in Dubai, they come over, they seem
incredibly grateful and understanding.
The propaganda in each of these countries
would tell them a number of things,
but they learned to discount it.
That's why they're so happy that Telegram
exists, is because the way they can
understand the world
around them is to receive
conflicting, mutually exclusive viewpoints
from sources that hate each other,
and try to understand what really is
true, because there's no such
thing as an unbiased source of
information. When the war
in Ukraine started in 2022,
I instantly realized
Telegram is going to be used
to spread propaganda by both sides,
and I didn't want Telegram to
be used as a tool for war.
I said, and I posted it publicly,
I suggested maybe we should just
suspend the activity of
all politics- related
channels in both countries
for the time of the war.
Maybe we shouldn't have channels
in these two countries.
And then, interestingly, people from
both countries revolted against this.
They told me, both people in Ukraine and in
Russia, that I don't get to babysit them
and decide for them what
sources of information that
they have to be granted access
to. They are grownups that can
make these decisions for themselves. They
understand that there
is a lot of propaganda.
They learn to see through this propaganda.
They learn to be able to tell truth from
lie. And in this time of war, it
was particularly valuable for them
to receive as much information as possible,
because their relatives, their friends
were getting affected and are
still getting affected. They
want to understand what was going on.
At that point, I realized people
are smart, people get it.
People can see through it. If you
ask most people in any of these
countries, "Do you agree that
access to Telegram should be restricted
for whatever reason?" They would say no.
- They hunger to have a voice.
- They need a voice and they need a
place to share their opinion securely.
- I have to ask you, on the
question of leadership in
the LaPointe interview, the journalist said
that you're often compared to Elon Musk.
And you highlighted some interesting
nuances around that, that you're
quite different; that Elon
runs several companies at once
while you only run one, and Elon can
lean more on the emotional
side while you deliberate and
think deeply before
acting. Can you expand on
this? Also, there's an interesting
point that you made that
everybody's weakness is also a strength.
Everybody's strength is also a
weakness. There's a dual nature to
all our characteristics. So, on the
topic of Elon, what have
you learned from his style
of leadership? What do
you respect about him?
- First of all, I don't think
there is such thing as
a negative personal
trait. In most cases, our
bad traits and our good traits are the
same trait or at least have the same
source. Of course, there are
some extreme examples, but
I'd say 99% of people, if you analyze
their character, their bravery can be seen
in recklessness in other situations.
Depending on circumstances,
you would see exactly the same personality
trait, and it would be either a good
thing or a bad thing,
because humanity is perfect
as a whole and each of us is different
for a reason. We have evolved to be
different, to complement each other's
abilities so that together we are invincible.
And even if you take a person
as complicated as Elon, I believe
that certain traits that Elon
demonstrates, that people
criticize about him, are
also the sources of his strength.
For example, his emotionality
is derived from the fact that
he cares about issues deeply
and he is willing to start as many
wars and as many fights as it takes
to change the world in the
direction that he thinks is right.
He also seems to be able
to extract motivation
from all these wars and personal conflicts,
which is, again, not something to be
underestimated. At a certain
point in the life of a
successful entrepreneur, the question of
motivation starts to be the primary
question. If we're talking about the most
richest person in the world and
the most famous entrepreneur in
the world, you have to wonder, how does
he motivate himself? And if starting
a war on X, debating certain issues,
or becoming personal with other CEOs,
criticizing them, if these activities help
Elon to innovate
and start new projects, he should be doing
more of it. There's nothing wrong in
being non-agreeable. Actually, it's
one of the main traits of a successful
entrepreneur, not agreeing with things.
And every time somebody like Elon... But
there is no somebody like Elon. There's just
Elon. I think, at least
from the entrepreneurs I
know and I personally interacted with,
he's unique in the sense that he keeps
launching new things,
running them in parallel,
and he doesn't seem to be stretched too
thin. Well, some people think he is, but
he manages to still demonstrate success
in all or most of his endeavors.
So again, you can criticize Elon for
being emotional, but would he be the
same person without this? I doubt that.
- and the incredible teams he's motivated
too. There's an element of that,
which you've spoken about. The
team at Telegram, you know,
assembling a team of A-players, as
we've talked about, is a skill
in itself. And that's also a
big part of the the leaders that
we've discussed, is like what,
judged in part by the team you assemble.
- Yes. And one of the necessary
character features to enable that is
to be ready to be unpleasant. You have
to be ready to insult some people
if their work is inferior.
You have to be ready to fire
them without remorse. So in order to be
an efficient and great entrepreneur
and enrich the world of innovations,
you have to do unpleasant things. Most
people will shy away from it. And
in a certain sense, entrepreneurs
sacrifice their peace of mind in order to
contribute to the world around them.
And Elon is a great example of that.
- I have to ask you about the
big picture of Telegram.
We've already talked about the
fact that you own 100% of it,
and there's a lot on the business side of
it. The business structure of Telegram is
fascinating. You've invested 100, maybe
hundreds of millions of dollars of your own
money. As far as I know, you
take a salary of what? $1?
- One dirham is one-third of that.
- One-third of a dollar. And
in 2024 was the first time
Telegram was profitable. So one
of the interesting questions is,
here, that we could talk for many hours
about, but I'd love to get a high-level
view picture. You've left what I
understand, what I think is a
huge amount of money on the table
by sticking to your principles. For
example, not doing advertisement
that's based on user private
data, which basically every
social media company does. So,
the only advertisement that
Telegram does is based on channels
and groups, based on the topic,
not the private data of the
individuals. And the other thing
is, which is also gangster
and incredible, is you
don't do a news feed, which
is the most addictive and
engagement-inducing aspect of social media,
which feeds the very kind of addictive
downside of the internet: the distraction,
the engagement drama, farming
aspect that we've talked about in the
very beginning that you try to resist,
that you think is damaging the human
mind at scale. So anyway, that's
just speaking to the fact that you're
leaving a lot of money on the table. So,
how the hell were you able to be
profitable? What are the ways that Telegram
makes money?
- Yeah. We had to innovate a lot in order
to reach a point where we are profitable
without having to resort to dubious
business activities involving
exploiting personal data of users,
something that most of our competitors do.
Because money has never been the primary
goal, at least not for me. When I sold
the remaining share of my first company,
I had to do it below market price because
I didn't leave Russia completely
without any pressures, you know?
I reinvested the vast majority
of everything in Telegram.
Telegram is an operation that is
losing money for me personally. I
never... I didn't extract more from
Telegram than I invested in it. I never
sold a single share.
But I also didn't want to sell Telegram,
so how do you reach a point when you're
profitable without
sacrificing your values?
One of the ideas we
explored was a subscription
model, but only for certain additional
features. We wanted to keep all the
existing features free, and just add
more business-related tools
or tools for advanced users
that they would have to pay for,
say, four or five dollars a month.
It was quite unprecedented at
the time. It wasn't considered
a viable option for messaging
apps to do that. We launched the
premium subscriptions
for Telegram in 2022,
and now we have over 15 million
paid subscribers. This is
some very significant recurring
revenue. So, we would
receive more than half a billion
dollars from premium subscriptions
alone this year, and it's growing fast.
For that, we had to innovate a lot. We
included over 50 different features
into the premium package.
And then, how do you
make an app that is already
more powerful than any other
messaging app on the market
even more useful so that people
would be ready to pay for this
extra? That wasn't easy.
That took a lot of effort.
- And you're constantly adding features.
- We're constantly adding features.
- That's actually fun to watch, just the
rate of adding... And some of them are
subtle, like the updates to improvements,
expansions of polls, for example.
- Yes. You keep improving the
existing features and adding new
ones, and every time when you add a new
feature, you don't want to clutter the app.
So, in a way, they're not in your
way. They're invisible. That's not an
easy thing to do. And most of the
features maybe are not even known
to the majority of our users. But
when you need them, they're there.
So, premium is one source of
our revenue. We also have ads,
but they're context-based, not
targeted. Of course, we leave probably
80% of value on the table because we are
not ready to engage in all those practices,
exporting personal data.
- Just to be clear,
targeted ads is what most
social media companies, most tech companies
that do any kind of advertisement
do, and that's the kind of advertisement
that uses personal data from users,
just to clarify. And when you
said 80%, that's a lot of money.
- Of course, because we would never
use, for example, your personal
messaging data, or your
contacts data, or your
metadata, or your activity
data to target ads.
It's sad that it became
synonymous with the internet
industry, this kind of
exploitation, but we are happy
with the fact that we managed to
make Telegram profitable despite
that. We're also experimenting a lot with
blockchain-based
technologies. We're the first
app to allow people to directly
own their username and
their digital identities using smart
contracts and NFTs, removing
Telegram from the picture.
So, for example, Telegram
cannot confiscate
your username from you. It's impossible.
We do a lot of things related to
the ecosystem of Telegram.
We have a thriving mini app
platform, millions of mini app developers
launching their own bots and applications.
- So, a lot of people are making millions
of dollars on the Telegram platform?
- Yes, we enable them to receive
payments from the users through in-app
purchase mechanisms provided by Apple and
Google, which I think was the
first attempt of this kind
to allow that both on iOS and
Android, and on a big platform, so
that third-party developers of
mini apps, which are basically
websites so deeply
integrated into Telegram
that you can't tell whether
they're standalone or
they're part of the overall
experience. And by providing this
payment option, we are able to extract a
commission from these transactions. But
it's a very low commission. Presently,
it's 5%. So we aren't greedy
here. We want people to succeed
in building these tools for our users. We
understand that mini apps bring us users.
The more users we have, the
more successful and relevant
Telegram becomes. We need
third-party developers. I think,
at this point, Telegram gives
developers, by far, the most powerful
tools to create.
- Plus, there's a bot API, and you
have to tell me about the TON
blockchain and the crypto
ecosystem available through
Telegram. So what is TON, also known
as, the Open Network Blockchain?
- TON is a blockchain technology that we
initially developed in 2018 and 2019,
and we started to develop it because
we needed a blockchain platform to
be integrated deeply into
Telegram because we believe in
blockchain. We think it's one
of the technologies that enable
freedom. But, at the time, if you look at
Bitcoin, if you look at Ethereum, they were
not scalable enough to
cope with the load that
our hundreds of millions of users would
create. They would just become congested.
And I asked my brother, "Can we
create a blockchain platform
that would be inherently scalable so that
no matter how many users or transactions
there are, it would split
into smaller pieces, which we
call shard chains, and
would still process all
transactions?" And he thought
for a few days and said,
"Yes, it's possible, but it's not
easy." When we started building it,
we ended up succeeding in developing that
technology, but we couldn't release it
because the SEC, the Securities
and Exchange Commission in the
United States was unhappy with the way
the fundraise for TON was
conducted. So we had to abandon the
project, and the open-source community
took over. Luckily, because we
constantly conducted those
contests with third-party
developers, there was a
thriving community around TON,
which now stood for The
Open Network as opposed to
its prior name, Telegram Open
Network. And so this project
got eventually launched without
our direct involvement, and it's
thriving now because everything we
do, like I said, is blockchain-based,
tokenized, usernames, Telegram accounts
are all based on TON and
its smart contracts.
It's the only way for third-party
developers and creators
to withdraw the funds that they
earn through our revenue-sharing
programs. For example, with
channel owners, we do a
50/50 split of ad revenues.
It's also the only way to
transact on Telegram. For
example, if you want to buy ads
on Telegram, you should use TON.
All the new things we launch, for
example, gifts that we mentioned
earlier, which you can define as a
reinvented socially relevant NFT
integrated into a billion-user ecosystem,
but at the same time, available on-chain,
transferable, which you can own
directly, also based on TON. Incredibly
fast-growing space. We only launched them
about half a year ago. And now as a result of
these Telegram gifts, TON has become, I
think, the largest or the second-largest
blockchain in terms of
daily NFT trading volumes.
- So, like you mentioned, it is a
Layer 1 technology as opposed
to being built on top of Ethereum
or Bitcoin. And it's able to
achieve the scale and the
speed of transactions that's
needed for something like
Telegram. And like you also
mentioned, the gifts.
You recently launched
some Snoop Dogg gifts. Are there going to
be some other celebrities in the pipeline?
- Yeah, I'm a big fan of Snoop, and
that's why when they reached out,
suggesting to do something together,
I said, "Let's launch some
Snoop-related gifts." And it was
really fun. We managed to sell
12 million worth of
gifts within 30 minutes.
- 30 minutes. Well, there you go.
I even got a few, but yeah.
- After this, we have many requests from
many really high-profile influencers
that, in a way, are lining up.
- So, from my perspective as a fan, it's just
interesting to see what kind of art you create for
any kind of celebrities,
athletes, musicians, because the
the Snoop, the Snoop gifts are all
just, like, going back to our previous
conversation, just beautiful pieces of art
that, like, encapsulate certain memes,
certain aspects of Snoop that everybody
knows. These cultural icons
that he represents. That's
cool. That's just... and they're,
the detail, the incredible
detail of the art of the individual
gifts is just incredible.
- And each of these gifts is scalable
because it's vector-based. It references
certain points in Snoop's creative
biography. And each of them has countless
different versions. We had to create
over 50 distinctive versions of each.
And then each individual piece is
unique because it also has unique
background, unique icon
in the background. It's
something that we reinvented because we
didn't like the old school
NFTs. First of all, they were
not relevant socially because, okay, you
have an NFT. Where do you demonstrate
it? In a Telegram, a Telegram gift is
there next to your name. It's
part of your digital identity on
Telegram. And then you can create
collections of gifts and show it off on your
profile page. But it also... The other
thing that we wanted to reinvent is
the aesthetic part of it.
Most NFTs are just ugly
and they're not based on any sophisticated
technology. So, what we did with
Snoop's gifts, I think
represents an example of
beautiful, aesthetically pleasing, and
at the same time very accurate in terms
of references to this
specific artist's biography,
a mixture between art and
technology, which I think is quite
rare. I'm quite proud of it. I
think it's a new trend, a new
phenomenon. It's only half a year old. So,
let's see where it goes. We're
gonna select our next influencer
or artist to be part of it.
- Hey, listen, I'm really proud I
got a Snoop gift next to my name
and I figured out that you can add
even more by pinning them. It's like a
cool little art icon.
- We didn't expect it, by the
way. We just had a lot of fun
launching these things
and then we realized
that one of the first collections we issued,
we sold each piece at something like
$5. And then the minimum price of any
items in these collections currently is
something like $10,000.
And it keeps going up.
So, I was quite surprised with the
reception. I realized, you know, when
you are trying to monetize a
social media platform in a way
that is consistent with your values, you're
forced to find ways that benefit your
users, not exploit them. People love these
gifts. People love the fact that they can
congratulate a person close to
them with something valuable
and at the same time something
beautiful. Also, some people
make a business out of it, which
is funny. They resell these
gifts. We recently met a guy who
earned several million dollars
just from buying and selling gifts.
- It's a real market.
- It's a real market. And it's just
something that he did in a few
months. And last year when we launched
many new features for the
mini apps on Telegram and,
payments options for them
and the other monetization
options, the same guy earned $12 million
from mini apps. And I
know several people who
anecdotally, like, "I earned
$10 million, I earned $3
million," just in a matter
of months single-handedly.
Sometimes they would have
a team of two, three
people. So, whenever I hear
stories from people who
were able to build businesses on top of
Telegram, this makes me incredibly proud.
- And mini apps include games,
they include tools, services of
any kind. It's an app within
the ecosystem of Telegram. Let
me ask you about crypto in general.
So, you've been an early supporter of,
cryptocurrencies, Bitcoin. You
bought into Bitcoin early on.
You kept buying. Maybe you could speak
to the reasoning why you
kept buying Bitcoin.
Do you think Bitcoin will go to a million
dollars? Do you think it'll keep increasing?
And Bitcoin and all the
other cryptocurrencies.
- I was a big believer in
Bitcoins since more or less the
start of it. I got to buy my
first few thousand of Bitcoin in
2013, and I didn't care much. I
think I bought it at the local
maximum. It's something like
$700 per Bitcoin, and I just threw a
couple millions there. And a lot of people
after Bitcoin, later next year, went
down, somewhere close to
300, 200, started to express
their sympathy to me. They say,
"Oh, you're a poor fellow. You made
this horrible mistake investing in this
new thing, but don't feel bad about it.
We still have some
respect for you." And I,
my response to them was, "I don't
care. I'm not going to sell
it." I believe in this thing. I
think this is the way money should
work. Nobody can confiscate your
Bitcoin from you. Nobody can
censor you for political reasons. This
is the ultimate means of exchange,
and again, I'm now talking
about Bitcoin but it relates to
cryptocurrencies in general.
So I have been able to fund my
lifestyle, so to say, from my Bitcoin
investment. Some people think
if I'm able to rent nice locations or
fly private, it's because I
somehow extract money from
Telegram. But like I said, Telegram is a
money-losing operation for me personally.
Bitcoin is something that allowed me to
stay afloat, and I believe it will come
to a point when Bitcoin is worth $1
million. Just look at the trends. The
governments keep printing
money like no tomorrow.
Nobody's printing Bitcoin. There is
a predictable inflation and then
it stops at a certain point.
Bitcoin is here to stay. All the
fiat currencies, remains to be seen.
- Let me ask you a deeply philosophical, serious
question. In your first Tucker interview
you had two interesting chairs
in the background. I think they
reference a now legendary meme the
choice is Пики точеные или хуи дрочёные.
What is the philosophical wisdom
in the dilemma that these two
chairs present? Have you had to face
the dilemma yourself personally?
- Not this exact dilemma. I think this is a
riddle that people have to face in Russian
prisons. And metaphorically,
it's describing all the situations
where you're presented a choice
between two suboptimal
options. When you're running
a big business or when you're
running a large country, it is
similar. You sometimes face this
dilemma. What are you going to do?
This very horrible thing
or this also very horrible
thing? So I think the right
answer to this riddle is
not to do any of these
things. Reframe the question.
Design a solution that turns a disadvantage
into an advantage, and then use it
to cope with the other
side of the problem.
So, do you know the answer to that riddle?
- No, somebody on the internet said: "Не ходи
туда, где задают такие вопросы." Which is
basically, "Try to avoid
the situations where such
dilemmas present themselves,
where there's no right answer."
- This is one of the ways
to answer this question.
If you got to a tricky situation, that
probably earlier you made a certain mistake.
- You fucked up already.
- It should have been avoided. But the
other quite creative answer to this
question is that you
is you take the sharp objects from
one of the chairs, or the spikes,
and then you use them to cut off
the objects from the other chair, and
you know what objects I'm talking about.
- That's a very engineering solution.
I'm glad somebody came up with that.
- I believe this is the right answer.
We're often being manipulated
by politicians, by corporate leaders, to
make a choice from two suboptimal options,
and then when we are forced to make the
choice, and we make the choice, it's
almost as if it's something that
we have to assume responsibility
for. I don't think we
should be buying into that.
- Okay, on this theme of absurdity
and ridiculousness, let
me... there's an object here that appeared
in the... Not many people seem to have
noticed this. People should go watch
your excellent conversation in
the Oslo Freedom Forum behind you. I'm
no archeologist, but I believe this is
a... well, how should I put it? A
walrus penis bone, and it was
behind you. You told me that you,
that you brought it with
you to France and back to
Dubai. I assume it brings you luck of some
sort. What's the... why did you bring
it with you everywhere? Is it kind of
like, you know, in America they have a
wishbone? Is it just a large wishbone?
Because a wishbone brings you luck.
And I should also point out that
just like with Telegram, with
the art, there's tiny little
walruses. And thanks to you, I had
to also find out that a lot of
mammals have a bone inside their
penis, and the evolutionary
advantage, I guess, of having a bone
is quite obvious. It actually raises
the question of why humans don't
have an actual bone inside their
penis. A lot of questions there.
- That's a very interesting subject. The reason
I have this is because a tribe that is
almost gone, extinct in
Siberia and Mongolia, called
Evenki, passed me this gift from them.
Normally, they would craft
something like this only for
their most respected leaders. It is supposed
to be a token of their appreciation
for bravery, courage, leadership.
Ironically, it also translates
in a very specific way into the Russian
language. In Russian, "walrus's penis" means
something a bit funny, which is often
used to describe nothing. So, for
example, if you've been requested
by, say, a certain government
or a certain business partner
to provide something that you are not
willing to provide, you can just politely
have this penis bone in the background
while you're doing the video call
and hope that they would-
- through osmosis, figure out the deep
message. It is an indirect rebellion.
By the way, in the former
Soviet Union, there was, and a
lot of places throughout history, some of
the rebellion had to take this kind of
symbolic, metaphoric form, through
poetry, through children's
stories. It's the beauty of
human language and art that
we're able to do that. Say "eff"
you to whatever forces that try
to overpower us. We say "eff"
you through poetry, through art,
and sometimes through a rather
large walrus penis bone...
carried by what appears to be
either a happy sumo wrestler
or a cat of some sort.
- They asked a lot of questions
about this walrus's penis bone
in the airport, both here in the UAE
and in France. They are always very
interested in this thing.
- Hmm. There seems to be some confusion
over how many kids you have.
It's often said to be over 100. Can
you explain how many kids you have?
- The truthful answer to this
question is I don't really
know how many biological kids I have
exactly, because at a certain point in my
life, about 15 years ago, I decided that
it was a good idea to be a sperm donor.
Initially, a friend of
mine asked me to help,
because they were trying to
have a baby with his wife, and
they experienced certain health issues
that prevented them to do it the
natural way. And he asked me,
he told me, "We don't want to
just rely on some random, anonymous
genetic material. We want somebody we know
and respect to be the biological
father of our kid." And I said,
"You gotta be kidding me. Sounds
ridiculous. What are you even
talking about?" But then
I realized it's, it's
actually a serious issue, and they were
not the only couple struggling with
that. So eventually, I got
persuaded into doing more of
it. I can't say I'm incredibly
proud of that, but I think it was
the right thing to do, particularly at the time
when I thought, "Okay, I probably don't have much
time on this planet left.
Things are getting trickier and
trickier, so if I can help some couples
have babies, let's do it." And then more
recently, when I was working on my will,
I realized that I shouldn't make
a distinction between the kids
conceived naturally and the kids who are
just my biological kids that I never
seen. As long as they can establish their
shared DNA with me, someday,
maybe in 30 years from
now, they have to be entitled to a share
of my estate after I'm gone. And that
made a lot of noise in the news for some
reason. People get very
excited by this kind of
news. I got a lot of messages from
people claiming they're my kids.
I got a lot of requests from
people asking me to adopt them.
The memes were priceless,
but understanding
that... no, it's not a
thing that most people do.
I don't see anything wrong with it. If
anything, I think more people should
be donating sperm.
- So, yeah, we should say that
the 100-plus kids is from
that, and you also have naturally conceived
kids. And it was a pretty bold decision
to, from a financial perspective,
to treat them all equally. And
also quite interesting was that you kind
of said that they don't receive any money
for the first few decades of their
life. Can you describe that thinking?
- Yeah, I think overabundance
paralyzes motivation and
willpower. It's extremely harmful,
particularly for young boys,
to grow up in an environment
where they can be proud, not of
their own achievements, but of
their father's achievements or their father's
wealth. This removes the incentive to
work on developing their own skills,
removes the incentive to study, to
work. So, I thought if
they're going to have this
money, it should be something
that they would only get
when they're already adult. It's
still risky. But one of the reasons I
decided it makes more sense to
divide this huge wealth that
I'm likely to leave behind among
100 or more than 100 people,
is that it won't be too much
for every single
descendant. But at the same
time, some people did the
calculation. It's still
many, many millions of dollars for each
child, so I'm not sure it helps too much.
- On the topic of abundance,
offline, we had a lot of
fascinating philosophical discussions,
one of which was about the mouse
paradise experiment, also known as
Universe 25. It's an experiment from
the 1960s and early 70s, conducted
by ethologist John B. Calhoun.
And we can talk about this
one for hours also, I'm
sure. But it was an experiment with a few
hundreds of individual mice compartments,
and they provided them with
unlimited food, water, nesting,
no predators, stable temperatures,
and frequent cleaning.
Basically, the definition
of abundance as far as mice
go. And the interesting
aspect of this experiment
is that at first the population
doubled, it grew very
quickly, but then it leveled off, and certain
really negative social things started
happening. Like mothers neglected or
killed their young. Violent attacks and
hypersexual activity became widespread.
Some "beautiful" ones, largely
inactive, well-groomed mice
withdrew, refusing to mate or
interact. So, all of these kind of
societal qualities that we see as
negative for the functioning of a
society started to emerge because
of the abundance, and finally the
collapse. The reproduction
rates crashed. Social
dysfunction spread to the next
generation and eventually just went
extinct. It didn't just
plummet to a low level,
it plummeted steadily to zero
despite the fact that there
was ongoing resource abundance. As
the description states, "The last mice
died surrounded by untouched food and
water." So, I mean, there's
deep wisdom to that
about abundance. It seems...
You've mentioned this in different
contexts throughout this
conversation, is it seems
like scarcity, it seems like
constraints, it seems like non-abundance
is essential for human flourishing,
which is a counterintuitive notion.
It's true for mice, and I think
it's probably true for humans too.
- We have evolved to overcome
scarcity. Almost by definition there
has never been such thing
as infinite amount of food
or entertainment in our lives before now.
We seem as a species to lose our ability
to identify purpose in a world where you
have everything, and everything loses its
meaning. Restrictions are important.
I think, though, that they should be
coming from within. It should be
self-restriction rather than restriction
in order to create purpose and meaning
in life. In a way, I was lucky in a very
counterintuitive way because I grew up
poor. I didn't have money when I was a
teenager. I had the same jacket for years,
which was bought on a second-hand
marketplace. My father wouldn't receive
his salary as a university
professor for months because
the Russian state was almost
bankrupt back then. My mom had to
juggle two jobs to take care of us. It was
not easy, but it also created purpose,
it created meaning, it created
priorities. It allowed us to focus
on things that mattered, allowed us
to develop our character and intellectual
abilities. Now, if we had everything...
why do anything? These mice...
suffered societal collapse that
was irreversible. And this
is not an accident. This kind of experiment
has been repeated countless times. At a
certain point, social dysfunction and
the erosion of social roles becomes
contagious, and the society
gradually degrades into a
chaotic collection of individuals
unable to take care of the next generation
or even to produce the next generation,
and it goes extinct.
- It's fascinating because we're creating
technologies, and this is what AI
is proposing to our future generations
as a problem to solve, which
is AI may very well
create abundance. And so
we will be like these mice
potentially, whether it's AI or
other kinds of technologies
that increase and give more and
more to all of us, and it is a thing
that will decrease the amount of
suffering in the world, increase the quality
of life. But as we reach towards that
abundance, the fabric that connects us,
rooted in our biology that's
developed by evolution
might create a real challenge for us.
- We should find the right balance
between chaos and order,
between self-restriction
and freedom for creativity.
- Your father recently celebrated
his 80th birthday. You had a
conversation with him.
He gave you some life
advice. I think you mentioned to me one
of the things he said was not to just
speak of your principles,
but to live them, to lead by
example. I think this is
something you already
do well. Maybe can you speak to what you've
learned about life from your father,
maybe some of the lessons he told you
in the conversation you had with him
on his birthday?
- I'm incredibly lucky to have my father.
He's a person who wrote countless books
on ancient Rome and ancient Roman
literature, dozens of
scientific papers, and I always
remember him working. He would be
busy typing his books and
articles on an old-school
typewriter back in the
late '80s, early '90s.
He was relentless. The example he
set to myself and my brother was
priceless. Some people make
this mistake of thinking that
you can instill the right principles
in the future generation or into
your kids by saying things to
them, but kids are smart. They discount
words; they look at the actions.
So observing our father was
a big lesson by itself.
It wasn't necessary for
him to say anything to us.
And then at the same time, he was
incredibly patient, emotionally
resilient. And, you know, my mom,
great woman, incredibly smart, highly
educated, but she would sometimes try to
test the patience of my father, and it's a
trait rooted in our biology. There's
an evolutionary explanation for that, that
women sometimes tend to do that. And he
demonstrated incredible patience all the
time. He told me recently, "You shouldn't
give the wrong example
to the people around you, and in
particular, to your kids, because
you can do the right
thing nine times out of
ten, but you make a mistake
once, and they will
instantly copy it. If you're
telling your kids not to use a
smartphone, but you're using a
smartphone all the time yourself
and coming up with all kinds of
sophisticated, brilliant explanations
why they shouldn't be using a smartphone,
it won't land. It's bound to fail."
So you lead by example. And
there are other numerous
lessons: staying positive,
looking at the bright side,
never despair, be honest. And, you know, he
told me last time I spoke to him that AI
can have consciousness, can be
creative, but it cannot have
conscience. In a way, it cannot
be moral. It cannot have
deeply rooted principles,
cannot have integrity
in the meaning that we
understand it as human beings.
- I love the fact that you're talking
to your 80-year-old father and
you're talking about AGI. And the
difference between human, the human
spirit, human nature and
what AGI, AI is able to
achieve, and conscience is the thing that
humans have. The ability to
know the right from wrong.
- This is the lesson that he gave me.
One of my goals in life is
never to disappoint him.
- Another thing we've talked
about, which I think is a
fascinating topic, is the power
of the mind, power of thought.
Do you believe you can
affect your life in reality
by thinking about it, by manifesting
it into being? What do you think?
- There are many explanations
why it works. One
thing most people agree on is that setting
goals and staying positive and confident
does allow you to achieve the
things you want to achieve.
It's very hard to believe,
though, that you can just
manifest things into being
without applying effort
in the direction that seems to be
logical. Maybe some people exist
that can just sit on the bank of a river
and materialize things by the power of
their thought, but I'm not sure I'm one of
these people. I always found it more
easy to believe that if you couple this
optimism and faith with logical action,
then it is bound to be successful.
- Prolonged effort, hard work coupled with
positive focus, thinking about the thing.
- Oh, yes, over many, many,
many days. It is possible
to imagine our world as a
high dimensional universe
where humans have the ability to
navigate through it with the power of
belief, which is coupled with
positive emotion and logical
thinking. But we are getting into
an esoteric realm. We don't
have any proof of that,
but we also know that we probably, at
this point, haven't discovered even 1%
about this universe.
- I agree with you fully, and I
like what you said in the way you
were thinking about it. You've told me
before that maybe there's a
way that with effort and with
a focused mind, you can
shape, you can morph the
sort of landscape of probabilities around
you, and it's a nice way to visualize
it, that somehow our effort
and our focus changes the things
that are likely and less likely, and
by focusing on it, we make the thing
more and more likely. At least as an
estimate, as a kind of field that we through
our thoughts and through our actions
change that field, and there's
eight billion of us doing so. And
together there's this collective intelligence
that creates the world we see around
us, like the mice. And like you
said, us as a humanity together are
perfect. I like that you said that.
- I admire your belief in the
fact that we get to experience
this together, because it's not obvious.
Maybe each of us experiences
his own or her own universe,
and maybe every second the universe
splits into a billion of different
universes, and everything that can happen,
happens. And there is a universe where,
say I died in 2013, maybe every time I
die I actually get to shift to a parallel
universe where I don't die and then
it keeps going and at certain points
we achieve this quantum immortality
when we are 1,000 years old,
but a lot of people from other versions
of reality think we are long gone.
- Yeah, this is something that you explained to me,
the idea of quantum immortality, which is a thought
experiment, which I find deeply
fascinating. People should look into it.
it. Which is very crisp, clean
consequence of the many worlds
interpretation of quantum mechanics,
that we as conscious beings can't
experience our death. We can
only... As we branch into these
many worlds, only the living
consciousnesses get to
experience it. So in some sense,
yeah, there's many universes. If we're to
seriously take the many worlds interpretation of
quantum mechanics, there's many universes where you
died many times, especially you. And I'm glad we're
in a universe where we get to share the table
we're the, in a universe where
we get to share the table
with this impressive bond,
a little humor and a lot of
serious topics covered today. Once again,
I can't say enough, a giant thank you from
me and a giant thank you from hundreds
of millions of people that follow your
work for you fighting for the freedom
of all of us to speak and creating a
platform where we can do so. And
thank you so much for talking
today, brother. It's been an honor
getting to know you and to be able
to call you a friend.
- Thank you for saying that.
I'm also incredibly grateful
to you and to the fact that I happen
to be in this version of reality.
When I haven't died, at
least yet. And hopefully
we'll get to spend more fun moments
in the years to come together.
- Thank you, brother.
Thank you for listening
to this conversation
with Pavel Durov.
To support this podcast,
please check out our
sponsors in the description.
And now, let me try
to articulate some things
I've been thinking about.
If you would like to submit
questions or topics like this
for me to talk about in the future,
go to lexfridman.com/ama.
I'd like to use this opportunity
to talk about Franz Kafka,
one of my favorite writers.
The reason he has been on my mind
is that his work, "The Trial,"
and the case of Pavel Duro in France
has, let's say, eerie parallels,
both metaphorically and literally.
Of course, "The Trial"
is a work of fiction,
but I think it is often useful
to go to the surreal world of literature,
even of the over-the-top dystopian variety
like "1984," "Animal Farm,"
"Brave New World," "The Trial,"
"The Castle," "Metamorphosis,"
even "The Plague" by Albert Camus,
all to better understand our real world
and the destructive paths
we have the potential to go down together,
which also hopefully helps us understand
how to avoid doing so.
So lemme zoom out and
speak about Franz Kafka.
Who was he?
He was an insurance
clerk who wrote at night.
He died young and almost
completely unknown,
and he asked for his
manuscripts to be burned.
Luckily for us, his friend, Max Brod,
refused to do so,
giving us the work of what I consider
to be one of 20th
century's greatest writers.
In his work, Kafka wrote
about the cold, machine-like reduction
of humanistic case files
through the labyrinth
of institutional power.
He wrote about an
individual's feeling of guilt
even when a crime has not been committed.
Or more generally,
he wrote about the feeling of anxiety
that is part of the human condition
in our modern, chaotic world.
His writing style was to use
short, declarative sentences
to describe the surreal and the absurd,
and in so doing, effectively, I think,
convey the feeling of an experience
versus simply describing the experience.
For example, famously,
his work, "The Metamorphosis"
opens with the following lines,
"As Gregor Samsa awoke one
morning from uneasy dreams,
he found himself transformed in his bed
into a gigantic insect.
He was lying in his
hard, armor-plated back,
and when he lifted his head a little,
he could see his dome-like brown belly
divided into stiff arched segments,
on top of which the bed quilt
could hardly keep in position
and was about to slide off completely.
His numerous legs,
which were pitifully thin
compared to the rest of his bulk,
waved helplessly before his eyes."
Kafka, I think,
effectively uses this image
of being transformed into a
giant bug stuck on his back
to convey a feeling of helplessness
and uselessness to his family,
to his job, to society.
The feeling of being a burden to everyone,
dehumanized, alienated, and abandoned,
the feeling of being
only temporarily valued
as long as he served some function
for his job or for his family,
and quickly discarded otherwise.
I will probably talk about
this work in more depth
at another time,
because it is so haunting
and I think it is such
a profound description
of the burden of existence
in modern society
for many people.
But here, lemme talk about
another of his work, "The Trial."
In this novel, the main
character, Josef K,
is a successful bank officer,
and he's arrested on his
birthday for an unspecified crime
by a kind of amorphous court
whose authority is everywhere and nowhere.
He navigates a labyrinth-like legal system
where everyone knows about his case,
but no one can really explain it.
The so-called trial
never actually occurs in
any conventional sense.
Instead, Josef K's entire life
becomes the proceedings
leading up to the trial.
In a sense, "The Trial" is the state
of being accused itself,
a permanent condition rather
than a singular event.
Kafka's genius in this work was to show
that modern institutions
don't need to hold trials,
they just need to hold you
in the permanent looming
possibility of one.
Public attention to this case,
both positive and negative,
gives Josef K a feeling
of constantly being judged
by people around him.
This wears at his mind
and his psychological wellbeing
begins to deteriorate.
In a sense, the trial
doesn't need to convict him.
The internal psychological turmoil
and the external social
scrutiny performs a conviction
and the eventual execution.
And exactly one year after his arrest,
Josef K is visited by two men
who walk him courteously through the city
to an abandoned quarry
and stab him in the heart,
without Josef K resisting.
To me, "The Trial" shows
that tyranny's final victory
isn't when it kills you,
but when you hold still for the knife,
not because you're forced,
but because you've been
exhausted into submission.
Once again, it is a haunting story
of the soullessness of bureaucracy
and its suffocation of the human spirit.
I highly recommend this short book,
and I'll probably talk about
it even more in the future.
I don't think it's
especially useful for me
to speak any parallels between "The Trial"
and Pavel Durov's case,
because after all, "The
Trial" is a work of fiction.
But on a positive note, let me
report that as far as I saw,
Pavel has maintained optimism
and a general positive outlook
throughout this whole process.
What I always fear in such cases
is that a bureaucratic
system can wear people down,
exhaust them into surrendering.
I saw none of that with Pavel.
I don't think he knows
how to give up or give in,
no matter how much pressure he's under.
Again, this is truly inspiring to me.
Also, now that we're talking about it,
let me mention some other of Kafka's work
that was moving to me, "The Castle."
A similar description as "The Trial" does
of the absurd inaccessibility
of those in authority
of the nightmarish bureaucracy.
The character in "The
Castle" is also named K.
Both bureaucracies operate
through exhaustion,
endless deferrals,
procedures, waiting rooms.
Again, highly relevant to modern times.
I can also highly recommend Kafka's
"In the Penal Colony" and "Hunger Artist."
Both are too interesting and weird
to explain in depth here.
But let me say, "The
Hunger Artist" is a story
that I think is relevant
to our modern-day attention economy,
where so many people want to be famous.
It tells the story of a,
let's say, professional faster
who performs starvation in
a cage as entertainment,
and he slowly loses his
audience to newer spectacles,
so much so
that eventually when he starves himself
to death, nobody cares.
Kafka's work is heavy.
It serves as a warning for the nightmare
that civilization can become,
and yet I think it is
also a source of optimism,
because when we can recognize elements
of our own world in Kafka's stories,
when we can see elements
of our institutions
in "The Trial" or in "The Castle,"
when we can see ourselves in Gregor Samsa,
we're not just diagnosing the disease,
we're proving that we're still human
and wise enough to see it and name it.
Kafka gave us the goal
to resist against such systems
that try to dehumanize us
and to ensure that individual freedom
and the human spirit keep flourishing.
I think it will.
I have faith in us humans.
I love you all.